Hello and welcome to The Tech Download - a new CNBC Original podcast where we
안녕하세요, The Tech Download에 오신 것을 환영합니다. CNBC Original의 새로운 팟캐스트로, 저희는
unpack the tech stories that matter most.
가장 중요한 기술 이야기를 풀어드립니다.
Each season, we dive into one big theme - and what it means for
매 시즌마다 하나의 큰 주제에 깊이 들어가, 그것이
your money - with insights from the industry's most influential voices.
여러분의 돈에 어떤 의미가 있는지, 업계에서 가장 영향력 있는 목소리들의 통찰과 함께 살펴봅니다.
I've always thought that, in the end, it would be the most important technology we'll
저는 늘, 결국 이것이 우리가
ever invent. And it's sort of the natural progression, really, of the computer age.
앞으로 발명할 것 중 가장 중요한 기술이 될 것이라고 생각해 왔습니다. 그리고 이는 사실 컴퓨터 시대의 자연스러운 진화이기도 합니다.
This season, we’re looking at Google DeepMind, the powerhouse driving the tech giant's AI push.
이번 시즌에는 거대 기술 기업의 AI 추진을 이끄는 핵심 동력인 구글 딥마인드(Google DeepMind)를 살펴봅니다.
We've been given rare access to key figures at the company - including
저희는 이 회사의 핵심 인물들에게 드물게 접근할 기회를 얻었는데, 여기에는
our guest for this episode DeepMind co-founder and CEO Demis Hassabis.
이번 에피소드의 게스트인 딥마인드 공동 창업자이자 CEO인 데미스 하사비스도 포함됩니다.
I think there it's going to be like the industrial revolution,
저는 이것이 산업혁명과 비슷할 것이라고 생각합니다.
but maybe 10 times bigger, 10 times faster. So,
하지만 아마 10배 더 크고 10배 더 빠를 것입니다. 그래서
it's incredible amount of transformation, but also disruption that's going to happen.
엄청난 변화가 일어나는 동시에 큰 혼란도 뒤따를 것입니다.
Hey everyone, and welcome to The Tech download. Allow me to reintroduce myself. I'm Arjun Kharpal,
여러분 안녕하세요, The Tech Download에 오신 것을 환영합니다. 다시 인사드리겠습니다. 저는 아르준 카르팔입니다.
Senior Technology correspondent at CNBC based in London, and I've
런던에 기반을 둔 CNBC 선임 기술 특파원이며,
got a very special new co host with me. Hey there, Arjun, yeah. Steve Kovach here,
저와 함께할 아주 특별한 새로운 공동 진행자가 있습니다.
I cover tech over here in New York. I mostly focus on Apple and Microsoft. But look,
저는 여기 뉴욕에서 기술 분야를 취재합니다. 주로 애플과 마이크로소프트를 다루지만, 그런데 말입니다,
I've been covering the tech industry for over 15 years now. I kind of have a good grasp on
저는 15년 넘게 기술 업계를 취재해 왔고,
everything. I'm so excited to be here with you, Arjun, because I've just admired your work from
전반적인 흐름을 꽤 잘 알고 있다고 생각합니다. 아르준, 이렇게 함께하게 되어 정말 기대됩니다. 저는 그동안
across the ocean for so long, and now we actually get to kind of collaborate and do this thing
바다 건너에서 오랫동안 아르준님의 일을 존경해 왔는데, 이제 실제로 함께 협업해 이 일을
together. I think it's gonna be a good time. It's going to be so fun. Steve. So between us,
함께하게 되었습니다. 즐거운 시간이 될 것 같습니다.
we think we've got nearly three decades of experience covering tech, and the crazy thing is,
저희는 기술을 취재해 온 경험이 거의 30년에 달한다고 생각하는데, 놀라운 점은
we've got so much to learn. And I think over the course of us doing this podcast, we're going
아직도 배울 게 정말 많다는 점입니다. 그리고 이 팟캐스트를 진행하는 동안
to learn so much, speak to so many interesting people, I’m so excited that this first series,
정말 많은 것을 배우고, 매우 흥미로운 사람들을 많이 만나게 될 것이라고 생각합니다. 이번 첫 시즌을
we're kicking off with an insight into Google Deep Mind, one of the world's leading AI labs as well,
세계 최고의 AI 연구소 중 하나인 구글 딥마인드(Google DeepMind)를 들여다보는 것으로 시작하게 되어 더욱 기대됩니다.
just for our listeners and our viewers, a quick intro, I guess, to Google DeepMind. It was a
청취자와 시청자 여러분을 위해, 구글 딥마인드(Google DeepMind)를 간단히 소개해 드리겠습니다. 딥마인드는
company founded in 2010 here in London, where I sit, as well. Very small company founded by three
제가 있는 이 런던에서 2010년에 설립된 회사였습니다. 세 사람이 세운 아주 작은 회사였고,
people, Demis Hassabis, is Shane Legg and Mustafa Suleiman, who's at Microsoft now, right, yeah.
창립자는 데미스 하사비스, 셰인 레그, 그리고 지금은 마이크로소프트에 있는 무스타파 술레이만이었습니다. 맞죠? 네.
And in fact, I interviewed him, nearly a year ago now, Mustafa Suleiman, he's basically doing
사실 저도 거의 1년 전에 무스타파 술레이만을 인터뷰했는데, 그는 기본적으로
what Demis is doing over at Google. And it's just kind of interesting to see how Google was
구글에서 데미스가 하는 것과 비슷한 일을 하고 있습니다. 그리고 구글이 어떻게
like this incubator, so to speak, for all of this top AI talent around the world, Demis obviously
말하자면 전 세계 최고 AI 인재들의 인큐베이터 같은 역할을 해 왔는지 보는 것도 흥미롭습니다. 데미스는 당연히
stuck around. He's running Deep Mind over there. What I also think is really interesting, though,
계속 남아 있었습니다. 그는 그곳에서 딥마인드(DeepMind)를 이끌고 있습니다. 그런데 제가 또 정말 흥미롭다고 생각하는 점은,
is just this AI moment, Arjun, we've been living through for the last three years, and how three
바로 지금의 AI 모멘텀 말입니다, 아르준. 우리는 지난 3년간 이를 겪어 왔고, 또 3년 전
years ago, chat GPT comes on the scene, and Google was kind of seen as under threat. They
챗GPT가 등장하면서 구글이 위협받는 것으로 여겨졌습니다. 구글은
went through this code red. They had to go through a bunch of reorganizations internally. Eventually,
이른바 '코드 레드'를 겪었습니다. 내부적으로 대대적인 조직 개편을 거쳐야 했습니다. 결국,
Demis came out on top as the leader of AI. And guess what? 2025 was a really interesting year
데미스가 AI 리더로 부상했습니다. 그리고 아시겠습니까? 2025년은 정말 흥미로운 해였습니다.
for AI over at Google, they kind of caught up, and in some ways, even surpassed what chat GPT was
구글의 AI에 있어서요. 구글은 어느 정도 따라잡았고, 어떤 면에서는 챗GPT가
already doing. And this is really interesting because the fundamental technology for all this,
이미 하던 것을 오히려 넘어섰습니다. 이게 정말 흥미로운 이유는, 이 모든 것의 근본 기술이
these large language models we've been talking about for so many years, started at Google,
우리가 수년간 이야기해 온 대규모 언어 모델 같은 기술이 구글에서 시작됐기 때문입니다.
and the perception was Google, let chat GPT kind of take that technology and run away with it. But
그런데도 구글이 그 기술을 챗GPT가 가져가 주도하도록 내버려 두었다는 인식이 있었습니다. 하지만
now, in my view, at least Gemini is pretty much on par, if not better, than chat GPT.
지금은 적어도 제 생각에는 제미니(Gemini)가 챗GPT와 거의 대등하거나, 오히려 더 낫습니다.
and Google Deep Mind is integral for this. I mentioned it was founded in 2010 Google
그리고 구글 딥마인드(DeepMind)가 여기에 핵심적인 역할을 합니다. 앞서 2010년에 설립됐다고 말씀드렸습니다. 구글은
actually acquired Deep Mind in 2014 I was very new into my career as a tech reporter
실제로 2014년에 딥마인드(DeepMind)를 인수했습니다. 당시 저는 기술 기자로서 경력이 막 시작된 때였습니다.
as well. Google paid around 400 million pounds for Deep Mind at the time in 2014
저도 마찬가지였습니다. 구글은 당시 2014년에 딥마인드에 약 4억 파운드를 지불했습니다.
about $540 million. It's a stake this day that could be worth 10s of billions,
약 5억4천만 달러였습니다. 오늘날에는 그 지분이 수백억 달러 규모일 수도 있고,
maybe hundreds of billions of dollars, according to some estimates today, and Deep Mind really is
일부 추정에 따르면 수천억 달러에 이를 수도 있습니다. 그리고 딥마인드는 정말로
very much responsible for Google's AI. We talk about Gemini, the chat bot, the AI
구글 AI의 상당 부분을 책임지고 있습니다. 제미니라는 챗봇, 그 AI는
that Google's released to consumers. This is powered so much by the technology coming
구글이 소비자에게 공개한 것이죠. 이것은 딥마인드에서 나오는 기술에 의해 크게 구동됩니다
out of Deep Mind. But even before all of this Deep Mind was having some big breakthroughs,
딥마인드에서 나온 기술이요. 하지만 그 이전에도 딥마인드는 몇 가지 큰 돌파구를 만들어냈습니다,
there was a big moment a few years ago when they released a system called Alpha Go. This was the
몇 년 전 알파고(AlphaGo)라는 시스템을 공개했을 때 큰 순간이 있었습니다. 이는
first computer program that was able to defeat a world champion in a game called Go. This is a very
바둑이라는 게임에서 세계 챔피언을 이긴 최초의 컴퓨터 프로그램이었습니다. 바둑은 매우
complex game, and it was seen at the time as one of the grand challenges of AI because it was such
복잡한 게임이고, 당시에는 AI의 거대한 도전 과제 중 하나로 여겨졌습니다, 왜냐하면 그것이 너무
a complex game with so many different combinations available. The other big breakthrough, of course,
가능한 조합이 너무나 많기 때문입니다. 또 다른 큰 돌파구는, 물론,
was was something called Alpha Fold. This was another AI system developed at DeepMind that
알파폴드(AlphaFold)라는 것이었습니다. 이는 딥마인드에서 개발한 또 다른 AI 시스템으로
could accurately predict 3d models of protein structures. And the idea is, here is, if you
단백질 구조의 3D 모델을 정확하게 예측할 수 있었습니다. 그리고 핵심 아이디어는, 만약
could do that, this may lead to some medical breakthrough. So this advancement of science
그렇게 할 수 있다면 의학적 돌파구로 이어질 수 있다는 것입니다. 그래서 이런 과학의 진전이
has been pretty core to what Deep Mind's been up to. And clearly it was a significant bet from
딥마인드가 해온 일의 핵심이었습니다. 그리고 분명 이는
Google more than 10 years ago, because it's helped turn Google into an AI world leader today.
10여 년 전 구글의 큰 베팅이었습니다. 이것이 오늘날 구글을 AI 분야의 세계적 선도 기업으로 만드는 데 도움이 됐기 때문입니다.
Yeah, that's exactly right now. What really struck me about Deep Mind, having watched them
네, 지금 말씀하신 대로 정확합니다. 오랫동안 지켜보며 DeepMind에서 가장 인상적이었던 것은
for so many years, is how rooted in science they were. They weren't necessarily trying
그들이 얼마나 과학에 뿌리를 두고 있었는지였습니다. 꼭 소비자 제품을 만들려 했던 것은 아니었고
to build consumer products like they do now. They were really trying to solve fundamental
지금처럼 소비자 제품을 만들려 했던 것도 아니었습니다. 그들은 정말로 과학의 근본적인
problems in science and really usher in this era of AI powered drug discovery, of other big,
문제들을 해결하고, AI 기반 신약 개발 시대와 그 밖의 거대한
complex problems like climate change. I know Demis talks about that a lot, and he's going
복잡한 문제들, 예를 들어 기후변화 같은 것들을 열어가려 했습니다. 데미스가 그 얘기를 많이 하는 것으로 아는데, 오늘도
to talk about that in your conversation as well. Arjun, absolutely. Steve, look, it's a great scene
대화에서 그 부분을 함께 다루실 겁니다.
set up for Deep Mind. So let's get into the conversation with its CEO, Demis Hassabis.
그런 점이 DeepMind의 기반을 마련했습니다. 그럼 CEO인 데미스 하사비스와의 대화를 시작해 보겠습니다.
Demis, thanks for joining me on the tech download. Appreciate it.
데미스, 테크 다운로드에 함께해 주셔서 감사합니다. 정말 감사드립니다.
Thanks for having us
초대해 주셔서 감사합니다.
Demis, we're going to try to get through a lot in our time here. But I want to start first with the
데미스, 오늘 시간 동안 많은 이야기를 다뤄보겠습니다. 하지만 먼저
technology itself. And we've been talking about AI, and we've been talking about the capabilities
기술 자체부터 시작하고 싶습니다. 저희는 AI와 그 역량에 대해 이야기해 왔고
and how they've been continuously improving as well. Now in the tech world, and there's a lot of
그것이 어떻게 지속적으로 개선되고 있는지도 논의해 왔습니다. 이제 기술 업계에서는
conversations about how good can these models get, how good can these systems get, and there's a lot
이런 모델과 시스템이 어디까지 좋아질 수 있는지에 대한 대화가 많고, 또
of debate around this idea of scaling laws for our for our listeners, you know, it's this idea of of
이른바 스케일링 법칙이라는 개념을 두고 논쟁도 많습니다. 청취자분들을 위해 설명하자면,
more compute, more data, bigger models eventually will lead to bigger systems as well. You said we
더 많은 연산 자원, 더 많은 데이터, 더 큰 모델이 결국 더 큰 시스템으로 이어진다는 생각입니다. 당신은
need to push scaling laws to the maximum. There's questions over now, are we hitting any kind of
스케일링 법칙을 최대한까지 밀어붙여야 한다고 말씀하셨죠. 그런데 지금은 이런
walls in terms of progress of those scaling laws, in terms of the ability for these models to get
스케일링이 발전하는 데 어떤 벽에 부딪히고 있는지, 이러한 모델들이 더
better, and just from you know, what you've been developing here at DeepMind, what are you seeing?
좋아질 수 있는 능력 측면에서 한계에 도달했는지에 대한 질문이 있습니다. DeepMind에서 개발을 진행해 오신 입장에서 무엇을 보고 계신가요?
Well, look, I think scaling laws are going very well, so we're definitely seeing increased
우선 스케일링 법칙은 아주 잘 작동하고 있다고 봅니다. 그래서 저희는 분명히
capabilities by putting in more compute, more data, and making these models generally larger,
더 많은 연산과 데이터, 더 큰 모델을 투입할수록 역량이 늘어나는 것을 보고 있고
so that trends continuing may not have been as fast as it was a couple of years ago. So there's
그 추세는 계속되고 있습니다만, 몇 년 전만큼 빠르지는 않을 수 있습니다. 그래서
some talk of diminishing returns and but there's a big difference between sort of no returns and
수확 체감에 대한 이야기도 나오죠. 하지만 아예 성과가 없는 것과
exponential and I think we're somewhere in the middle where there's very good returns, and
기하급수적인 성장은 큰 차이가 있고, 저는 그 중간 어딘가에서 여전히 매우 좋은 성과가 나오고 있다고 생각합니다. 그리고
that's worth doing. On top of that, if I you know in terms of, like, getting all the way to AGI,
그럴 가치가 있습니다. 게다가 AGI, 즉
artificial general intelligence, you know, maybe that there's one or two big innovations still
범용 인공지능까지 가려면, 아직 한두 가지 큰 혁신이
needed as well, and maybe missing, in addition to the scaling up of kind of the existing ideas
기존 아이디어를 스케일업하는 것 외에도 필요하고, 어쩌면 아직 부족할 수도 있습니다.
We'll get on to AGI very shortly. But what are missing in your view?
AGI 이야기는 곧 더 하겠습니다. 하지만 당신의 관점에서 무엇이 부족하다고 보시나요?
Well, if you look at, I mean, we've all, you know, played around with different chat bots,
예를 들어, 우리 모두 여러 챗봇을 직접 이것저것 써 보셨을 텐데요.
and you can see that, you know, they can do very impressive things in some dimensions,
그러면 어떤 면에서는 매우 인상적인 일을 해낸다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
but they're kind of like jagged intelligences I like calling them in the sense of like,
하지만 저는 그것들을 일종의 '들쭉날쭉한 지능'이라고 부르는데, 즉
they're very good at certain things. But there are other things that they don't do they're not
어떤 것들은 매우 잘합니다. 하지만 다른 어떤 것들은 그들이 하지 못하고, 그들은
capable of at all. And and if you pose a question in a certain way, you find that they're flawed
전혀 할 수가 없습니다. 그리고 질문을 특정한 방식으로 던지면, 결함이 있다는 것을 알게 됩니다.
and they can't do some relatively simple things. And so for a true general intelligence,
그리고 비교적 간단한 일들도 하지 못합니다. 그래서 진정한 범용 지능이라면,
you shouldn't see that inconsistency should be consistent across the board. And also they're
그런 불일치가 보이면 안 되고, 전반적으로 일관돼야 합니다. 또 이런 것들은
things like it can't continually learn it can't learn new things online. It can't
지속적으로 학습하지 못하고, 온라인에서 새로운 것을 배우지도 못합니다. 그리고
truly create original things. So there's quite a few capabilities that you would like to see and
진정으로 독창적인 것들을 만들어내지도 못합니다. 그래서 보고 싶은 능력들이 꽤 많고,
you would need for general intelligence that are missing from today's systems.
범용 지능을 위해 필요하지만 오늘날의 시스템에는 빠져 있는 것들이 있습니다.
That's really interesting. So what would be the sort of unlock to get to those Intelligent
정말 흥미롭습니다. 그렇다면 그런 지능형 시스템에 도달하기 위한 핵심 열쇠는 무엇일까요?
Systems? I just want to quickly discuss the conversation I had with Thomas Wolfe,
제가 허깅페이스 공동 창업자 토마스 울프와 나눴던 대화를 잠깐 말씀드리고 싶습니다.
who's the co founder over at Hugging Face. Yes, he was talking to me a few months back
네, 몇 달 전 그가 저와 이야기를 나누면서
about his view on LLMs, in particular, large language models. And just saying,
LLM, 특히 대규모 언어 모델에 대한 자신의 견해를 들려주며 이렇게 말했습니다.
they're really great. And you know, you use these chat bots, and the chat bots say, hey,
그는 그것들이 정말 훌륭하고, 이런 챗봇을 쓰면 챗봇이 이렇게 말한다고 했습니다.
great question, great idea. And here's, here's all the information you need to know. But what's
"좋은 질문입니다, 좋은 아이디어입니다. 그리고 필요한 정보는 여기 모두 있습니다."라고요. 하지만 부족한 것은
missing is the ability for these systems to come up with new and novel ideas, perhaps,
아마도 이런 시스템들이 새롭고 참신한 아이디어를 스스로 떠올리는 능력이라는 점입니다.
and particularly, I know you're so interested in science and what AI could do to unlock new
그리고 특히 당신께서 과학과 AI가 무엇을 할 수 있는지에 큰 관심이 있으시다는 것도 알고 있는데요,
drugs or discover new diseases, etc, that actually maybe the LLMs limitations are
예를 들어 AI가 새로운 약물을 개발하거나 새로운 질병을 발견하는 등에서 돌파구를 여는 일 말입니다. 그런데 실제로 LLM의 한계가
there that can't come up with these Nobel Prize winning ideas, these novel ideas.
바로 그런 노벨상급의 참신한 아이디어를 만들어내지 못한다는 데 있는지도 모릅니다.
Yeah.
네.
So perhaps there needs to be some sort of new architecture. What's
그래서 어쩌면 어떤 새로운 아키텍처가 필요할지도 모르겠습니다.
your what's your thinking on that at the moment?
그에 대해 현재 어떻게 생각하십니까?
Well, look, my passion for and my whole reason I spent my whole career on AI is, I think,
제 열정이자 제가 AI에 커리어 전체를 바친 이유는, 제가 보기에 AI가
eventually will be the ultimate tool for science. And of course, we've shown that with things like
결국 과학을 위한 궁극적인 도구가 될 것이라고 생각하기 때문입니다. 그리고 물론 우리는
Alpha Fold and all of the science work we've been doing over the last decade. But there's still a
알파폴드와 지난 10년간 해온 다양한 과학 연구로 그 점을 보여주었습니다. 하지만 아직도
long way to go in terms of, can an AI actually come up with a new hypothesis itself, not just
AI가 실제로 스스로 새로운 가설을 세울 수 있느냐는 측면에서는 아직 갈 길이 멉니다. 단지
solve a conjecture that is already out there, which would be already useful and impressive. But
이미 존재하는 추측을 해결하는 것만으로도 유용하고 인상적이겠지만,
can it actually come up with a new conjecture, a new a new idea about how the world might work? And
실제로 새로운 추측, 즉 세상이 어떻게 작동하는지에 대한 새로운 아이디어를 스스로 떠올릴 수 있느냐는 것입니다. 그리고
so far, these systems can't do that. They don't really have the capability to do that. So there
지금까지 이런 시스템들은 그것을 하지 못합니다. 그런 능력이 충분하지 않습니다. 그래서
seems to be something missing. I think, some of the capabilities that required a kind of long term
무언가가 빠져 있는 것 같습니다. 제 생각에는 장기적인
planning, better reasoning, maybe also the idea of a world model. This idea of, like, you know, the
계획 수립, 더 나은 추론, 그리고 아마도 '세계 모델'이라는 개념 같은 역량이 필요합니다. 즉,
system actually understanding better the physics of the world, so that it can run simulations,
시스템이 세상의 물리 법칙을 더 잘 이해해, 머릿속에서 시뮬레이션을 돌릴 수 있도록 하는 것입니다.
kind of in its mind to test its own hypotheses. You know, these are things that you know the best
자기 가설을 시험하기 위해서입니다.
scientists do, human scientists do. And so far, our AI systems, you know, are not able to do that.
이런 일은 최고의 과학자들, 즉 인간 과학자들이 하는 일입니다. 그런데 지금까지 우리의 AI 시스템은 그런 일을 하지 못합니다.
Can you just help us understand a bit more of this idea of world models? Because it may be
이 '세계 모델'이라는 개념을 조금 더 이해할 수 있도록 설명해 주실 수 있을까요?
a term people are hearing for the first time. You know how that gets they different differ from LLMs
많은 분들이 처음 듣는 용어일 텐데, 이것이 LLM과 어떻게 다른지 설명해 주시겠습니까?
So LLM's, and the models we use at the moment are, you know, mostly around text. Of course,
LLM과 현재 우리가 사용하는 모델들은 대체로 텍스트 중심입니다.
things like Gemini, our foundation model, can also cope with images and video and audio, so different
물론 우리 기반 모델인 Gemini 같은 것은 이미지, 비디오, 오디오 등도 처리할 수 있어 다양한 모달리티를 다룹니다.
modalities. But it's still actually understanding the physics of the world, the causality of the
하지만 여전히 세계의 물리와 인과관계를 실제로 이해하는 문제는 남아 있습니다.
world. You know, how one thing affects another thing? Can you plan a long time into the future?
예를 들어 한 가지가 다른 것에 어떻게 영향을 미치는지, 먼 미래까지 계획할 수 있는지 같은 것들입니다.
These are all related concepts, and if you really want to understand how the world works,
이것들은 모두 연관된 개념이며, 세계가 어떻게 작동하는지 정말로 이해하려면
so that maybe you can invent something new in the world, or explain something about the world that
세상에 새로운 것을 발명하거나, 이전에는 알려지지 않았던 세계의 어떤 것을 설명할 수 있어야 합니다.
was not known before, which is basically what scientific theory does, then you have to have
그것이 기본적으로 과학 이론이 하는 일인데, 그러려면
this, this accurate model of how the world works, you know, starting with intuitive physics and
세계가 어떻게 작동하는지에 대한 정확한 모델이 필요하며, 직관적 물리에서 시작합니다.
and how the physics of the world works, but all the way up to biology, you know, and economics.
그리고 세계의 물리가 어떻게 작동하는지에서 시작해 생물학과 경제학까지 아우르게 됩니다.
And do you envisage the world if we get of artificial general intelligence,
그렇다면 인공 일반 지능, 즉 AGI에 도달하게 된다면 세상을 어떻게 그려 보십니까?
is sort of human level of intelligence, that that there will be a combination of llms and
AGI는 대략 인간 수준의 지능인데, 그때 LLM과 세계 모델이 결합해 함께 작동하게 될까요?
world models working together, or will sort of world models supersede, in some sense, LLMs
아니면 어떤 의미에서는 세계 모델이 LLM을 대체하게 될까요?
No, I think there'll be some convergence of these technologies. That's at least my betting is, is
아니요, 저는 이런 기술들이 어느 정도 수렴할 것이라고 봅니다.
there will be these LLMs, or foundation models, you know, like Gemini under the hood, that will
내부에는 Gemini 같은 LLM, 즉 기반 모델이 깔려 있을 것입니다.
be a key component. I think the question, I think there's almost no doubt about that in my mind,
그것이 핵심 구성 요소가 될 것입니다. 그 부분은 제게 거의 의심의 여지가 없습니다.
which is why we must try and scale those systems as as as big and as as powerful as we can. But
그래서 우리는 그 시스템들의 규모를 가능한 한 크게, 그리고 강력하게 키우려고 해야 합니다.
the question is, is, is it the only component that's needed for an AGI and that's where I think,
하지만 문제는, AGI에 그것만이 필요한 유일한 구성 요소인지 여부입니다.
I suspect other types of technologies and other types of capabilities will be needed. And I think
그리고 저는 다른 종류의 기술과 다른 역량들도 필요할 것이라고 생각합니다.
these world model capabilities, and we're working on our versions called Genie and and we have video
이런 세계 모델 역량과 관련해 우리는 'Genie'라고 부르는 버전도 개발 중이며, 비디오 모델도 보유하고 있습니다.
models like VO, state of the art, video models that you can generate videos from, in from text,
VO 같은 최첨단 비디오 모델은 텍스트에서 비디오를 생성할 수 있습니다.
and you can think of video models and interactive models like Genie as kind of, you know, early
또 비디오 모델과 Genie 같은 인터랙티브 모델은 일종의 초기 단계의 세계 모델로 볼 수 있습니다.
embryonic world models, where, if you can generate something that's realistic about the world, then
초기 단계의 세계 모델에서는, 세계에 대해 현실적인 무언가를 생성할 수 있다면,
in a sense, your model understands that about the world. Otherwise, how could it have generated it?
어떤 의미에서는 모델이 그 세계를 이해한다는 뜻입니다. 그렇지 않다면 어떻게 생성했겠습니까?
Demis, you mentioned this, AGI, artificial general intelligence. I know there's various
데미스, 방금 AGI, 즉 인공 일반 지능을 언급하셨는데요.
definitions of it floating around. You've previously said you believe that reaching
그 정의가 여러 가지로 제각각인 것으로 압니다.
AGI could be somewhere in the in the realm of five to 10 years away. Is this still your view,
이전에 AGI가 5~10년 안에 올 수도 있다고 보신다고 하셨는데,
given, I guess, some of the profound developments we've seen in 2025
2025년에 본 큰 진전들을 감안해도 지금도 그 견해가 유효합니까?
Yes, I think we're right on track from that. Actually, when we started DeepMind
네, 저는 그 전망대로 잘 가고 있다고 생각합니다. 사실 DeepMind를 시작했을 때
back in 2010 we thought this would be a 20 year kind of mission to build AGI,
2010년 당시에는 AGI를 만들기 위한 20년짜리 임무가 될 거라고 생각했습니다,
you know, a system that's capable exhibiting all the cognitive capabilities we have, including,
즉 우리처럼 모든 인지 능력을 발휘할 수 있는 시스템인데요, 예를 들어
you know, things like true innovation and creativity and planning and reasoning and
진정한 혁신과 창의성, 계획 수립, 추론 같은 것들 말입니다.
things like that. And I think we're about five to 10 years away from that, but that's,
바로 그런 것들입니다. 그리고 저는 그 목표까지 대략 5~10년 정도 남았다고 보는데,
you know, pretty incredible, if you think about how transformative a technology this is
이 기술이 얼마나 변혁적인지 생각하면 정말 놀라운 일입니다.
You mentioned there might need to be some more technology breakthroughs. We're seeing
추가적인 기술적 돌파구가 더 필요할 수도 있다고 하셨는데요. 지금 우리는
things like the models advancing. We're seeing the semiconductors advancing rapidly as well.
모델이 발전하는 것도 보고 있고, 반도체도 빠르게 진전되는 것을 보고 있습니다.
Are there any currently bottlenecks and things you need to figure out?
현재 병목이 되거나 해결해야 할 과제는 무엇인가요?
I know energy is something that's been brought up so much saying, Well, look,
에너지는 계속 거론되는 주제인데요, 예를 들어 "말씀드리자면,"
we can keep advancing chips, we can keep advancing models, but at some point we're
칩은 계속 발전시키고 모델도 계속 발전시키겠지만, 어느 시점에서는 우리는
just not going to have enough energy to run these data centers, to run these AI models.
이 데이터 센터와 AI 모델을 돌릴 만큼의 에너지가 부족해질 수 있다는 얘기입니다.
Yeah, yeah. Well, ook, there's, there's lots of physical constraints. So of course, there's,
네, 네. 음, 그러니까 물리적 제약이 많이 있습니다. 물론,
you know, no one ever has enough chips. And you know, we're lucky that we have,
그 누구도 칩이 충분했던 적은 없습니다. 다행히 우리는
you know, our own TPU range, in addition to GPUs and but there just aren't enough
GPU뿐 아니라 자체 TPU 라인업도 갖추고 있지만, 그래도 결국 부족합니다.
compute chips in the world, really, for the demand. And of course, in the end,
전 세계적으로 수요를 감당할 만큼의 연산 칩이 충분하지 않습니다. 그리고 결국
that comes down to energy as well. There's this idea of energy will be effectively is
그 문제는 에너지로도 귀결됩니다. AGI 시대로 갈수록 에너지가 사실상
synonymous with intelligence as we get into the era towards AGI. Now, the interesting thing is,
지능과 동의어가 될 것이라는 생각도 있습니다. 그런데 흥미로운 점은,
I think the AI itself will help here, in the sense of getting more efficiencies out of existing
AI 자체가 여기서 도움이 될 것이라는 점입니다. 기존
infrastructure, but helping with things like material design better better solar materials,
인프라의 효율을 끌어올리는 것뿐 아니라, 소재 설계나 더 나은 태양전지 소재 같은 것에도요.
but it could also help with new breakthrough technologies like fusion. We, you know,
또한 핵융합 같은 새로운 돌파구 기술에도 도움이 될 수 있습니다. 우리는
we have a collaboration with Commonwealth fusion in the US to help contain plasma and fusion
미국의 Commonwealth Fusion과 협력해 플라즈마를 가두고 핵융합
reactors. And one of my pet projects is, can we come up with a room temperature superconductor
원자로를 제어하는 데 도움을 주고 있습니다. 제 개인적 프로젝트 중 하나는 AI로 상온 초전도체
material using AI? So I think there are multiple breakthroughs that AI could come up with and help
소재를 만들어낼 수 있느냐는 것입니다. 그래서 AI가 제안하고 우리가 함께 만들 수 있는 돌파구가 여러 가지 있다고 봅니다.
us come up with that would help with the energy situation. In fact, indeed, that's,
그런 것들이 에너지 상황을 개선하는 데 도움이 될 것입니다. 실제로 그건,
I think that's one of the most promising use cases of AI. And then the other thing is,
제 생각에 AI의 가장 유망한 활용 사례 중 하나입니다. 또 다른 점은,
as these systems are getting better, they're also getting, you know, 10x more efficient per year.
이 시스템들이 좋아질수록 매년 효율도 대략 10배씩 개선되고 있다는 것입니다.
So if you look at our range of models, we have our kind of Lighthouse model, our Pro versions
예를 들어 우리 모델 라인업을 보면 Lighthouse 모델과 Gemini의 Pro 버전이 있고
of Gemini, but then we have our flash versions, which are way more efficient, and the sort of
또 훨씬 효율적인 Flash 버전도 있으며,
workhorse models that are used for everything, and they use techniques like distillation, where
여러 용도로 쓰이는 주력 모델도 있습니다. 이들은 지식 증류 같은 기법을 쓰는데,
you have a big model that teaches a smaller model, and the smaller model is really, really efficient.
큰 모델이 작은 모델을 가르치고, 그 작은 모델이 정말 매우 효율적으로 동작하는 방식입니다.
And I think there are more and more innovations and techniques like that that will keep bringing
그리고 그런 혁신과 기법들이 점점 더 늘어나면서
the efficiency curve down, and so you get, you know, much better performance per per watt.
효율 곡선을 계속 낮춰, 와트당 성능이 훨씬 좋아질 것입니다.
We hear a lot about sort of AGI, and I think there's a lot of people wondering, technology,
AGI 이야기를 많이 듣는데요, 많은 분들이 이 기술이 얼마나 대단한지 궁금해합니다.
sounds amazing, sounds great. There's also a lot of fear right around the proliferation of
정말 놀랍고 훌륭하게 들리지만, 이 기술이 널리 퍼지는 것에 대한 두려움도 큽니다.
this technology and the impact it's going to have on on people every day and their lives.
그리고 그것이 사람들의 일상과 삶에 미칠 영향에 대한 우려도 큽니다.
I guess for you, what are some of things we need to consider,
당신 입장에서는 우리가 고려해야 할 것들이 무엇인지,
yeah
네.
from from that perspective, in terms of the impact on society, whether it's around jobs,
그 관점에서, 일자리 같은 사회적 영향 측면에서,
whether it's around kind of what we're going to do with our time if we reach this goal, versus,
이 목표에 도달하면 시간을 어떻게 보낼지 같은 문제든,
I guess, the benefits that you believe this technology is going to bring for humanity?
아니면 당신이 이 기술이 인류에 가져올 것이라고 믿는 이점이든요?
Well, of course, you know, I believe that overall, AI is going to be one of the most
물론 저는 전반적으로 AI가 인류가 발명한 가장
beneficial technologies humanity ever invented. That's why I spent my whole career working on it.
유익한 기술 중 하나가 될 것이라고 믿습니다. 그래서 제 경력 전체를 그것에 바쳤습니다.
But it's only, you know, it's not a given. It's a dual purpose technology. I dream about using
하지만 그게 저절로 보장되는 것은 아닙니다. 이는 양면적인 기술입니다. 저는
AI for things like curing diseases. We have a spin out called isomorphic that builds it on,
질병을 치료하는 것 같은 일에 AI를 쓰는 꿈을 꿉니다. 아이소모픽이라는 스핀아웃이 있는데,
on Alpha fold work on protein folding, work that we did a few years ago to accelerate drug
알파폴드의 단백질 접힘 연구, 우리가 몇 년 전에 했던 그 작업을 기반으로 해서
discovery and try and solve all disease. I think that's now, you know, within reach, that type of
신약 발견을 가속화하고 모든 질병을 해결하려고 합니다. 저는 이것이 이제,
thing in the next decade or two. We've discussed energy. There's many benefits, I think AI is going
향후 10~20년 안에 그런 일이 가능해질 것입니다. 에너지 이야기도 했는데, AI가 가져올 이점은 많다고 봅니다.
incredible benefits AI is going to bring. But there are also risks. Obviously, there's kind
AI가 가져올 놀라운 이점이 많습니다. 하지만 위험도 있습니다. 분명히
of economic disruption, and I think there it's going to be like the industrial revolution, but
경제적 혼란이 있을 것이고, 이는 산업혁명과 비슷하겠지만
maybe 10 times bigger, 10 times faster. So, you know, it's incredible amount of transformation,
아마 10배 더 크고 10배 더 빠를 것입니다. 그래서 엄청난 변화가 일어나지만
but also disruption that's going to happen. And you know, we need some new economic models,
동시에 큰 혼란도 뒤따를 것입니다. 그리고 아마 새로운 경제 모델이 필요합니다
probably for that. And then on terms of the the worries about the usage of AI, I have two which I
아마도 이를 위해서요. 그리고 AI 사용에 대한 우려로는, 제가 걱정할 만하다고 보는 두 가지가 있는데
think are worth worrying about. One is bad actors repurposing these general purpose technologies,
그중 하나는 악의적 행위자들이 이러한 범용 기술을 다른 용도로 전용하는 것입니다
AI technologies, for harmful ends. And then the second one is AI itself, as it we get towards
즉 AI 기술을 해로운 목적에 사용하는 것입니다. 그리고 두 번째는 AGI로 다가갈수록 AI 자체입니다
AGI and agent based systems. So these are systems that are able to do things more autonomously than
그리고 에이전트 기반 시스템으로 갈수록 그렇습니다. 이는 오늘날의 시스템보다 더 자율적으로 일을 하는 시스템입니다
than today's systems. They can, you know, what are the guardrails around that? How do we make
이런 시스템은 더 자율적으로 행동할 수 있습니다. 그렇다면 그에 대한 가드레일은 무엇이며, 어떻게
sure we can keep them doing the things that we want them to do, and not veer off into something
우리가 원하는 일을 계속 하게 하고, 우리가 의도하지 않은 방향으로 벗어나지 않게 할 수 있겠습니까
that we didn't expect. And so those are the two kind of risks that are kind of that I foresee.
예상치 못한 무언가로 향하지 않도록요. 그래서 제가 예견하는 위험은 대체로 이 두 가지입니다
Do you feel that you've got systems that, or you're
그런 시스템을 이미 갖추고 있다고 느끼십니까, 아니면
developing systems that you can be in control of?
통제할 수 있는 시스템을 개발하고 있다고 느끼십니까?
I think we're, we're very confident about that. You know, we've had and thought about
저희는 그 점에 대해 매우 확신하고 있습니다. 아시다시피 저희는
responsibility and safety and security of these systems in the very beginning. You know,
아주 초기부터 이 시스템의 책임, 안전, 보안에 대해 생각해 왔습니다
we started DeepMind back in 2010 almost no one was working on AI back then. But
2010년에 딥마인드를 시작했을 때만 해도 당시에는 거의 아무도 AI를 연구하지 않았습니다. 하지만
we planned for success, and we knew success would mean these extremely powerful systems.
저희는 성공을 전제로 계획했고, 성공이란 이런 극도로 강력한 시스템을 뜻한다는 것을 알고 있었습니다
So we also understood the the other side of the coin of that. So from the very beginning,
그래서 그에 따른 동전의 다른 면도 이해했습니다. 그래서 처음부터
we've tried to be very thoughtful use the scientific method and a scientific approach
과학적 방법과 과학적 접근을 활용해 매우 신중하게 접근하려고 노력해 왔습니다
to try and understand as much about our systems we're building before we deploy them. Of course,
배포하기 전에 우리가 만드는 시스템을 가능한 한 많이 이해하려고요. 물론
that doesn't mean we won't make any mistakes. There's two, it's, it's,
그렇다고 해서 실수를 전혀 하지 않는다는 뜻은 아닙니다. 또한 이것은
it's such a incredible and fast moving technology. But I think with with something like AI,
정말 놀랍고 매우 빠르게 움직이는 기술입니다. 하지만 AI 같은 경우에는
we need to be, you know, I call myself a kind of cautious optimist. I'm, I'm very big believer in
우리는 신중해야 합니다. 저는 스스로를 '신중한 낙관론자'라고 부르며, 저는
human ingenuity. I think given enough time and care, we'll get this right as scientists and
인간의 창의성을 굳게 믿습니다. 충분한 시간과 주의를 기울인다면 과학자로서도
as a society. But it's, it's not a given, and so we shouldn't be sort of rushing into this
사회로서도 우리는 이 일을 제대로 해낼 것이라고 봅니다. 하지만 그것은 당연한 일이 아니니, 너무 서둘러서는 안 됩니다
yeah
네
and we need to go into it with our eyes open.
그리고 우리는 눈을 뜨고 이 일에 들어가야 합니다
Because, I guess the reason I asked, because I know you've spoken to people like Yoshua, Bengio,
제가 이렇게 여쭌 이유는, 요슈아 벤지오 같은 분들과도 대화하신 것으로 알고 있기 때문입니다
Max Tegmark, and these are people I've also spoken to and and they're of this cohort that please do
맥스 테그마크도요. 저도 그분들과 이야기해 봤는데, 그분들은 '제발'이라고 할 정도로
do we need to be rushing so quickly into a world of AGI and agentic systems? Maybe we need more
AGI와 에이전틱 시스템의 세계로 그렇게 빨리 달려들 필요가 있느냐는 입장입니다. 어쩌면 더
tool based AI AI to solve specific things, rather than these all purpose or general
만능형 또는 범용 시스템보다, 특정한 문제를 해결하는 도구 기반 AI가 더 필요하다고도 합니다
purpose kind of systems? And I know they've called for, for perhaps a slowdown to the
그런 시스템 말입니다. 그리고 그분들이 아마 이런 AGI 시스템 개발 속도를
development of of these AGI systems. In your view, do you think you should be slowing down?
늦추자는 주장도 해왔다는 것을 압니다. 당신의 견해로는, 속도를 늦춰야 한다고 보십니까?
Well, I've had lots of you know, I know them very well, Yoshua And Max, we've had
음, 저는 그분들을 잘 알고 있고, 요슈아와 맥스는 특히 잘 압니다. 저희는
many discussions and many others. And actually, I have some sympathy for that view, that, you know,
많은 논의를 해왔고 다른 많은 분들과도 논의했습니다. 그리고 사실 저는 그 견해에 어느 정도 공감합니다
building a tool based AI is, you know, thinking of AI as a tool, or the ultimate tool for,
도구 기반 AI를 만든다는 것, 즉 AI를 도구, 혹은 궁극의 도구로 바라보는 것이
say, science is the right way to build AI in the initial stages. And certainly that's the way we're
예를 들어 과학을 위해서는 초기 단계에서 AI를 만드는 올바른 방식이라고 생각합니다. 그리고 분명 그것이 저희가
viewing it, and the kinds of things we apply AI to, like Alpha Fold. But the thing is, you know,
바라보는 방식이며, 알파폴드처럼 AI를 적용하는 방식이기도 합니다. 하지만 문제는
it's a very complex geopolitical and corporate system that we're in. And it isn't just about,
우리가 처한 환경이 매우 복잡한 지정학적·기업적 시스템이라는 점입니다. 그리고 이것은 단지
you know, there are many companies trying to build this. There are also many nations trying to build
많은 회사들이 이를 만들려고 한다는 것만의 문제가 아닙니다. 많은 국가들도 이를 만들려고 합니다
it. And it's, there's a sort of race dynamic, which I ideally wouldn't be there. So in an
그래서 일종의 경쟁 구도가 있습니다만, 저는 이상적으로는 그런 구도가 없었으면 합니다. 그래서
ideal case, this would be a scientific endeavor, and it will be very carefully, each step would be
이상적인 경우라면 이것은 과학적 시도가 될 것이고, 각 단계는 매우 신중하게
carefully considered. But unfortunately, the the prac that the real world isn't isn't like that,
검토될 것입니다. 하지만 안타깝게도 현실 세계는 그렇지 않습니다
and we have to kind of be pragmatic about where we are. So what we're trying to do is be good
그래서 우리는 현재 상황에 대해 실용적으로 접근해야 합니다. 그래서 저희가 하려는 것은
role models for Yes, being on the frontier, pushing that the benefits of that as quickly
좋은 본보기가 되는 것입니다. 최전선에서 그 이점을 가능한 한 빠르게
as we can and as broadly as we can, but also try and be as responsible as possible with that along
그리고 가능한 한 넓게 확산시키되, 그 과정에서는 가능한 한 책임감 있게
the way and thoughtful as possible. And I think we've got that balance pretty, pretty good right
또한 가능한 한 신중하게 하려는 것입니다. 그리고 저희는 그 균형을 현재 꽤 잘
now. And hopefully that's a bit of a role model to the rest of the field in the industry, too.
맞추고 있다고 생각합니다. 이것이 업계와 분야의 다른 이들에게도 작은 본보기가 되길 바랍니다
Yeah I want to address some of those dynamics as well. But just just first,
네, 그런 역학도 다루고 싶습니다만, 먼저
I guess, just from a personal point of view. Have you ever you said you
개인적인 관점에서 여쭙고 싶은데요. 예전에 말씀하신 적이 있듯이
sort of started this mission of Deep Mind? You know, you believe in the technology,
딥마인드라는 미션을 시작하셨다고 하셨잖아요. 기술을 믿고 계시지만,
but has there ever been any moments in your career when you're like, should we be doing this?
경력 중에 “우리가 이걸 정말 해야 하나요?”라고 생각한 순간이 있으셨습니까?
Look you when you look at how powerful the technology is, I really think that there
기술이 얼마나 강력한지 보면, 저는 정말로
are so many challenges confronting society today, not to do with AI, climate, poverty,
오늘날 사회가 직면한 도전이 너무 많다고 생각합니다. AI와는 별개로 기후, 빈곤,
you know, the access to water, there's a there's just so many issues health,
물 접근성 같은 것들요. 건강 문제도 있고,
aging, population, disease. So like, you know, energy we talked about earlier. So if a some,
노화, 인구, 질병도 있습니다. 그리고 아까 이야기했던 에너지 같은 것도요. 그래서 만약
if I if there wasn't a technology transformative as AI coming down the road,
그러니까, 앞으로 AI만큼 변혁적인 기술이 등장하지 않는다면,
I'd be really worried about society's ability to deal with these challenges.
사회가 이런 도전들을 감당할 수 있을지 저는 정말 걱정될 것입니다.
So interestingly, AI itself is one of those challenges, maybe one of the greatest ones,
흥미롭게도 AI 자체도 그런 도전 중 하나이며, 어쩌면 가장 큰 도전일 수도 있지만,
but it's also one which can help us cope with and resolve and solve some of these other big,
동시에 이런 거대한 문제들 가운데 일부를 우리가 견디고 해결하도록
grand challenges. So it's a very interesting one, right? It's sort of double edged, and I've always
도와줄 수도 있습니다. 그래서 흥미롭지요. 일종의 양날의 검이고, 저는 늘 그렇게
believed in that. I've always thought that, in the end, it would be the most important technology
믿어 왔습니다. 결국 이것이 우리가 발명할 가장 중요한 기술이 될 것이라고 생각해 왔습니다.
we'll ever invent. And I think it's sort of the natural progression, really, of the computer age.
그리고 이것은 사실 컴퓨터 시대의 자연스러운 진전이라고 생각합니다.
Demis, you just, just a quick aside, you started life in gaming, which is amazing.
데미스, 잠깐만요. 게임 업계에서 커리어를 시작하셨다니 정말 놀랍습니다.
Yeah, codeveloping theme park.
네, “Theme Park”를 공동 개발했습니다.
Yes,
네,
fantastic, fantastic game as well. Did you ever do you still play games?
정말 멋졌습니다. 훌륭한 게임이기도 했고요. 아직도 게임을 하십니까?
Yes, I love games. It's my hobby really well, like these days, like League of Legends,
네, 저는 게임을 정말 좋아합니다. 제 취미입니다. 요즘은 “리그 오브 레전드” 같은 것을
with my two boys and my brother and we have a little team. We've done it since lockdown.
두 아들과 제 형제와 함께 작은 팀을 꾸려서 하고 있는데, 봉쇄 기간부터 계속해 왔습니다.
But, yeah, I love games in all its forms from football to video games
하지만 네, 저는 축구부터 비디오 게임까지 모든 형태의 게임을 좋아합니다.
in such a high impact, stressful role as you have, potentially, is that your unwind?
그처럼 영향력도 크고 스트레스도 큰 역할을 하시는데, 게임이 긴장을 푸는 방법이 되십니까?
It is, it is, I would say so. And it's also, you know, it's,
그렇습니다, 그렇습니다. 그렇게 말씀드릴 수 있습니다. 그리고 또, 아시다시피,
it's a kind of in the past as well, has been a great creative endeavor for me,
과거에는 저에게 훌륭한 창의적 도전이기도 했습니다,
you know. And it's how I learned programming and other things was, was through making games.
게임을 만들면서 프로그래밍과 다른 것들을 배웠기 때문입니다.
I have nowhere near as stressful job as you but that's my unwind too,
저는 선생님만큼 스트레스가 큰 직업은 아니지만, 저도 그게 긴장을 푸는 방법입니다.
for sure.
확실합니다.
Get home, turn the console on.
집에 가서 콘솔을 켭니다.
Exactly, exactly
맞습니다, 맞습니다.
Just in that small segment alone, Steve, there's so much to unpack, and I want to focus on on two
그 짧은 구간만 봐도요, 스티브, 짚어볼 게 정말 많습니다. 지금은 두 가지
kind of big buzz words right now. The first is artificial general intelligence, or AGI,
큰 유행어에 집중하고 싶습니다. 첫 번째는 범용 인공지능, 즉 AGI입니다,
this idea, and I know there's so many different definitions of it, but broadly speaking, this
이 개념 말인데요. 정의도 정말 다양하지만, 대체로는
idea of AI that that is as smart or smarter than humans. And I think that so many of these big AI
인간만큼 똑똑하거나 인간보다 더 똑똑한 AI라는 개념입니다. 그리고 많은 대형 AI
labs, including Open AI, including Deep Mind, are pushing and hoping to get to this stage of AGI,
연구소들, 예를 들어 OpenAI나 딥마인드 같은 곳들이 그 AGI 단계에 도달하려고 밀어붙이며 기대하고 있습니다,
and so far, they've approached this with a technique called large language models,
그리고 지금까지는 “대규모 언어 모델”이라는 기법으로 여기에 접근해 왔고,
these AI models that are trained on huge amounts of data, but mainly text. But there's this other
이 AI 모델들은 방대한 데이터로 학습하지만 주로 텍스트입니다. 그런데 또 다른
buzzword, right? World models, this idea of these AI models that understand the physical world.
유행어가 있지요. “월드 모델”, 즉 물리 세계를 이해하는 AI 모델이라는 개념입니다.
And this is this. This buzzword is really growing in popularity, right?
그리고 이 유행어가 정말 인기를 끌고 있지요?
Yeah. And I think this is going to be a big theme of AI going into the rest of 2026,
네. 그리고 이것이 2026년 남은 기간 동안 AI의 큰 주제가 될 것 같습니다,
and even into next year. Because the idea here is that, LLMs, sure we got the language part down.
심지어 내년까지도요. 왜냐하면 핵심은 LLM이 언어 부분은 확실히 해냈다는 점이기 때문입니다.
It can mimic the way humans talk and speak and write and things like that. But when it comes to
사람이 말하고 쓰는 방식을 흉내 낼 수 있지요. 하지만
the physical world, you know, we talk so much about robotics and AI and physical AI, well,
물리 세계에서는 로보틱스와 AI, 물리적 AI를 많이 이야기하는데,
they need to understand how the physical world works, how water flows, how air moves and things
그런 시스템들은 물이 어떻게 흐르고 공기가 어떻게 움직이는지 등 물리 세계가 어떻게 작동하는지 이해해야 합니다.
of that nature, and what really struck out to me when you brought this up to Demis he said, Yeah,
그리고 제가 이 얘기를 데미스에게 꺼냈을 때 가장 인상적이었던 건 그가 “맞습니다”라고 했다는 점입니다,
we do need to start exploring that more. And in fact, he sees a world in which the LLM and those
더 탐구해야 한다고 했고, 실제로 그는 LLM과 그런
world models start to converge. I think that was the word he used, converge into something more
월드 모델이 서로 수렴한다고 보았습니다. 그가 쓴 표현이 ‘수렴’이었는데, 더
unique and more powerful and capable. This is also a debate that's been playing out among AI leaders,
독특하고 더 강력하며 더 역량 있는 무언가로 이어진다는 뜻입니다. 이런 논쟁은 AI 리더들 사이에서도 벌어지고 있고,
like on social media, you could fire up X or your favorite social media site, and what really struck
소셜 미디어에서도요. X나 좋아하는 소셜 미디어를 켜보면, 제가 특히 눈에 띈 사람은
out to me is Yann LeCun. He was the head of AI for many years over at Meta. He recently left to start
얀 르쿤입니다. 그는 메타에서 오랫동안 AI를 총괄했는데, 최근에는
his own thing, because he kind of got superseded by Alexander Wang and that whole big talent wars
알렉산더 왕과 지난여름 벌어진 대규모 인재 전쟁 속에서 자신이 밀려났다고 느껴, 결국 독립해 자기 일을 시작했는데요,
that happened over last summer, he had a really interesting interview in the Financial Times,
지난여름 벌어진 그 인재 전쟁 이후 파이낸셜 타임스와 아주 흥미로운 인터뷰를 했습니다,
he doesn't think LLMs are what's going to get us to AGI, to your point, that's what everyone's
그는 LLM이 우리를 AGI로 이끌 핵심이 아니라고 보며, 말씀하신 대로 모두가 그것을
chasing. The super intelligence AGI, whatever you want to call it. His thing is LLMs can only
쫓고 있습니다. 초지능 AGI든 뭐라고 부르든 간에요. 그의 요지는 LLM은
get you part of the way. You need world models and all sorts of other things. And he kind of
길의 일부만 갈 수 있다는 것입니다. 월드 모델과 온갖 다른 것들이 필요하다는 것이고, 그는
harshly criticized meta for not thinking beyond the LLM and that seems to be part of the reason
LLM을 넘어 생각하지 않는 메타를 꽤 강하게 비판했는데, 그것이
why he left to do his own thing. And it's really interesting to see one of Meta's big competitors,
그가 떠나 자기 일을 하게 된 이유 중 일부인 듯합니다. 그리고 메타의 큰 경쟁자 중 하나인
Gemini, just talk openly about it and say Demis saying, Yeah, we need to do this. We
제미니가 이를 공개적으로 이야기하며 데미스가 “그래요, 이걸 해야 합니다. 우리는
need to start thinking about this. It enables so many things, from robotics, autonomous driving
이제 이런 방향을 고민하기 시작해야 합니다”라고 말하는 것을 보는 것이 흥미롭습니다. 이는 로보틱스, 자율주행
and just a better understanding for these AI models and intelligent systems that we're
등 많은 것을 가능하게 하고, 우리가 대화하는 이런 AI 모델과 지능형 시스템을 더 잘 이해하도록 도와
chatting with to get you that right answer. Steve, do you ever use a chat bot and you
정확한 답을 내놓게 합니다.
put something in and it will say, Hey, Steve, great question. That's a really clever thought
무언가를 입력하면 “스티브, 좋은 질문입니다. 정말 기발한 생각입니다”라고 말하곤 합니다.
All the time. That's all that's that. It's the sycophancy of all these chatbots, right,
항상 그렇습니다. 그게 전부입니다. 이런 챗봇들의 아첨이죠, 그렇지 않습니까?
where they're like, Oh, you're so smart and great at asking me these questions. Yeah, all the time,
그러면서 “와, 정말 똑똑하시고 이런 질문을 해주시는 게 대단합니다”라고 합니다. 네, 늘 그렇습니다,
Exactly Because the reason I bring that up is partly to this point, this growing criticism
맞습니다. 제가 이 이야기를 꺼낸 이유는 부분적으로 바로 이 지점, 즉 LLM에 대한 점점 커지는 비판 때문입니다.
of LLMs is that actually, yes, they're great and they'll give you the information. But actually,
LLM에 대한 비판은, 물론 훌륭하고 정보를 제공하긴 하지만, 실제로는,
when it comes to LLMs as a foundation for being able to create new ideas,
LLM을 새로운 아이디어를 만들어낼 수 있는 기반으로 삼는 문제에서는
novel ideas, there's limitations there, and I think that's partly what Demis was
참신한 아이디어를 만들어내는 데 한계가 있으며, 이는 부분적으로 데미스가
speaking to and why this idea of world models is really growing in popularity.
말하고자 했던 바라고, 그래서 ‘월드 모델’이라는 개념이 인기를 얻고 있다고 생각합니다.
It's going to be interesting to see how this plays out, as you mentioned, into this next phase of AI,
말씀하신 대로, 이것이 AI의 다음 단계에서 어떻게 전개될지 지켜보는 것이 흥미로울 것입니다,
where it's key for things like robotics, driverless cars, and many other use cases too.
로보틱스, 무인 자동차, 그리고 다른 많은 활용 사례에서도 핵심이 될 것이기 때문입니다.
Yeah, and you'll you'll notice, as we continue this podcast, I am incredibly cynical about the
네, 그리고 이 팟캐스트를 계속 들으시면, 저는 지금 우리가 살고 있는 이 AI 순간의 로보틱스 측면에 대해 굉장히 냉소적이라는 점을 느끼실 겁니다,
robotics angle of this AI moment we're living in all that so many of the robots we're seeing,
우리가 보는 로봇들 중 많은 것들이
they're literally puppets. They're tele operated. The best example, of course, is the Tesla Optimus
말 그대로 꼭두각시입니다. 원격 조종됩니다. 물론 가장 좋은 예는 테슬라 옵티머스
robot, which started out as a man in a body suit dancing around. Now it's a real robot,
로봇인데, 처음에는 바디수트를 입은 사람이 춤추는 모습에서 시작했습니다. 지금은 진짜 로봇이지만,
but again, it's tele operated. There are literally people at a control room controlling it over the
그래도 여전히 원격 조종입니다. 관제실에 있는 사람들이 실제로 그것을
internet and even using their voice to talk to you and things like that. So we are , the
인터넷으로 조종하고, 심지어 목소리로 당신에게 말을 걸기도 합니다. 그래서 우리는,
robotics people I talked to, we had one in the office just a couple weeks ago, and they said the
그래서 제가 만난 로보틱스 업계 사람들은 불과 몇 주 전에도 사무실에 한 대를 가져왔는데, 그들이 말하길
hardest part isn't building the actual robot, it's training it, and that's where these world models
가장 어려운 건 실제 로봇을 만드는 것이 아니라 훈련시키는 것이며, 바로 그 지점에서 이런 월드 모델이
are going to come in, so they can actually operate autonomously, like we've been promised. Perfect.
필요해질 것이라고 했습니다. 우리가 약속받아 온 것처럼 실제로 자율적으로 작동하게 하기 위해서입니다. 좋습니다.
Demis, you mentioned some of the dynamics at play, right? And competition commercially, of course,
데미스, 작동하는 여러 역학을 언급하셨죠? 그리고 물론 상업적 경쟁도
is one of those. We've got Open AI, we've got Anthropic, we've got all these different AI labs
그중 하나입니다. 오픈AI도 있고, 앤스로픽도 있고, 이런 다양한 AI 연구소들이
out there. It's intense. And Gemini three has had such good reception so far. But there was
밖에 있습니다. 치열합니다. 그리고 지금까지 제미니 3는 반응이 아주 좋았습니다. 하지만
a point people were doubting Google as a whole and its ability to compete. And I'd
한때 사람들은 구글 전체와 그 경쟁 역량을 의심했습니다. 그리고 저는
say a point. It was at some point in 2025 and it wasn't that long ago. And then, you know, Gemini
그런 시점이 분명히 있었다고 말씀드리겠습니다. 2025년 어느 때였고 그리 오래전도 아니었습니다. 그리고 나서, 아시다시피, 제미니
3 really came out and impressed a lot of people as well. But it's a space that's ever changing.
3가 제대로 나오면서 많은 사람들을 놀라게 했습니다. 하지만 이 분야는 계속 변합니다.
So how we how would you assess right now, the competitive environment? How do you feel it?
그렇다면 지금 경쟁 환경을 어떻게 평가하시겠습니까? 체감은 어떠신가요?
Yeah, well, look, it's a ferocious, competitive environment at the moment. I mean, many people
네, 지금은 매우 치열한 경쟁 환경입니다. 많은 사람들이
were telling me, you know, being in tech for 2030, years, say it's that it's the most intense
제게 말하더군요. 기술 업계에서 20~30년 일해온 사람들이, 이게 가장 치열한
environment they've ever seen, perhaps, you know, ever in the technology industry,
환경이라고요. 어쩌면 기술 산업 역사상 가장 치열한 환경일지도 모릅니다.
and, and, and, you know, all the, I guess, most capable players, whether it's individual,
그리고, 그러니까, 가장 유능한 플레이어들이 모두, 개인이든
you know, tech Titans or big tech companies, and all the best startups, they're all involved in
기술 거인이든 빅테크 기업이든, 최고의 스타트업이든, 모두가
this space now, because I think everyone has understood what we've known for 20 plus years
이제 이 분야에 참여하고 있습니다. 모두가 우리가 20년 넘게 알고 있던 사실을 이해했기 때문이라고 생각합니다.
now that this is really the most important technology. So that's sort of to be expected,
즉 이것이 정말 가장 중요한 기술이라는 점입니다. 그래서 어느 정도 예상된 일입니다,
but it's tough, but it's, it's also exciting. And, you know, going back to games, I sort of,
하지만 어렵기도 하고, 동시에 흥미롭기도 합니다. 그리고 게임 이야기로 돌아가면, 저는 좀,
I've started playing chess when I was very young for the England Junior chess team. So I've kind of
저는 아주 어릴 때 잉글랜드 주니어 체스 대표팀에서 체스를 두기 시작했습니다. 그래서 저는 어느 정도
been brought up in in competition. So, you know, I love competition, fortunately, in fact, many
경쟁 속에서 성장해 왔습니다. 그래서 다행히도 저는 경쟁을 좋아합니다. 사실 많은
ways I live for competition. So a lot of a big part of me sort of like, likes to lean into this.
면에서 저는 경쟁을 위해 산다고 할 정도입니다. 그래서 제 큰 부분은 이런 상황에 더 뛰어들고 싶어합니다.
But on the other hand, the only thing I would say is, at the back of my mind, I know there's
하지만 다른 한편으로, 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 것은 이것입니다.
something much more important than individual competition between companies or even countries,
마음 한켠에서는 기업 간, 심지어 국가 간의 개별적인 경쟁보다 훨씬 더 중요한 무언가가 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
which is overall getting stewarding AGI well, for the world, for the whole, you know, for the all of
그것은 전 세계를 위해, 전체를 위해, 인류 모두를 위해 AGI를 제대로 관리하고 이끌어 가는 일입니다.
humanity. And I think that's incumbent of all of us who are leaders of the AI labs and and can have
그리고 AI 연구소를 이끄는 리더들이며 이에 영향력을 행사할 수 있는 우리 모두에게는 그런 책임이 있습니다.
an influence over this, is to have that sort of in the front of their minds, in amongst this sort
그런 관점을 늘 최우선에 두고 염두에 두는 것이 책무라고 생각합니다.
of ferocious capitalist competition that we're in as well. So both are true at the same time
우리가 처한 치열한 자본주의적 경쟁 속에서도 말입니다. 그래서 두 가지는 동시에 모두 사실입니다.
I mentioned, kind of the moment people were questioning what Google was going to do
앞서 사람들이 올해 초 AI와 관련해 구글이 무엇을 할지 의문을 제기하던 시점을 말씀하셨는데,
with with AI at earlier in the year. Yeah. Did you do anything different?
네. 그때 무엇을 좀 다르게 하셨습니까?
Yeah, I think I feel like, you know, if we go back over the last decade, actually, you know,
네, 지난 10년을 되돌아보면,
Google, Google Brain, specifically the research division in Google and DeepMind as it was.
구글의 연구 조직인 구글 브레인과 당시의 딥마인드는 비교적 독립적이었습니다.
Are sort of fairly independent. We kind of invented about 90% of the technologies
또 우리는 오늘날 모두가 사용하는 기술의 약 90%를 사실상 발명했습니다.
that everybody's using today, you know, whether it's transformers, of course, most famously,
예를 들어 트랜스포머가 그렇습니다. 물론 가장 유명한 사례입니다.
the architecture behind all the LLMs or AlphaGo, you know, sort of introduced reinforcement
모든 LLM의 기반이 되는 아키텍처라든지, 알파고처럼
learning at scale on a really hard problem. So we've invented all this technology, but then
정말 어려운 문제에서 강화학습을 대규모로 적용해 보인 것들이 있습니다.
maybe we were, in hindsight, we were a little bit slow to commercialize it and scale it. And
이런 기술을 모두 발명해 놓고도, 돌이켜보면 이를 상용화하고 확장하는 데는 조금 느렸던 편이었습니다.
you know, that's what Open AI and others did very well. And then the last two, three years,
그 부분은 오픈AI와 다른 곳들이 매우 잘 해냈습니다.
I think we've had to come back to almost our startup or entrepreneurial roots and be scrappier,
그리고 지난 2~3년 동안은 거의 스타트업, 혹은 창업가적 뿌리로 돌아가 더 치열하게, 더 민첩하게 움직여야 했습니다.
be faster, ship things really quickly and and sort of make really rapid progress. And
더 빨라지고 제품을 정말 신속히 출시하며 빠른 진전을 이뤄야 했습니다.
I think what you're seeing over the last couple of years, culminating in Gemini, the Gemini series,
지난 몇 년 동안 여러분이 보신 변화는 제미니로 정점에 이른 제미니 시리즈로 이어졌습니다.
which we're very happy with Gemini three is, as you mentioned, our latest version has sort of put
우리가 매우 만족하는 제미니 시리즈의 최신작인 제미니 3가, 말씀하신 것처럼,
us back, you know, near the top of, you know, the top of the leaderboards, where we feel we belong.
우리를 다시, 우리가 있어야 한다고 느끼는 리더보드 최상단 가까이로 올려놓았습니다.
And you feel like you can stay there.
그리고 그 자리를 계속 지킬 수 있다고 보십니까?
I feel like we can stay there, of course, yeah.
네, 물론 지킬 수 있다고 생각합니다.
Amid all this competition, there's obviously a lot of talk about bubbles in AI, yes, particularly
이런 경쟁 속에서 AI 거품에 대한 이야기도 분명히 많습니다.
around valuations of certain companies, companies rating raising astronomical sums of money. The
특히 일부 기업들의 기업가치를 둘러싸고, 기업들이 천문학적 자금을 조달하고 있습니다.
tech giant spending hundreds of billions on infrastructure, and companies out there,
거대 기술 기업들은 인프라에 수천억 달러를 지출하고 있습니다.
quite frankly, raising large sums of money with very little product, or even very little
그리고 밖에서는 기업들이, 솔직히 말해, 제품이 거의 없는 상태에서도 큰돈을 조달하고 있습니다.
profitability, if any. And so where do you think we are right now in terms of this, this
심지어 수익성이 거의 없거나, 설령 있다 하더라도, 막대한 자금을 조달하고 있습니다.
kind of bubble discussion? Do you think we're in a financial bubble when it comes to AI industry?
그래서 이 거품 논의에서 지금 우리가 어디쯤에 있다고 보십니까? AI 산업이 금융적 거품에 있다고 생각하십니까?
I think, I think it's not a binary thing, this bubble discussion. I don't I think
제 생각에는 이 거품 논의는 이분법으로 볼 문제가 아닙니다.
some parts of the industry might be in a bubble. To me, that's what it looks like,
산업의 일부는 거품일 수도 있다고 봅니다. 제게는 그렇게 보입니다.
and others probably not. You know, fundamentally, AI is going to be the most transformative
다른 부분은 아마 그렇지 않을 것입니다. 근본적으로 AI는
technology ever invented. So that's that's that part that underpins everything. So in the end,
인류가 발명한 것 중 가장 변혁적인 기술이 될 것입니다. 이것이 모든 것을 뒷받침합니다.
it's a bit like the internet bubble. In the end, the Internet was critical, and there were
그래서 결국 인터넷 거품과 비슷합니다. 인터넷은 결국 핵심이었습니다.
some generational companies that were created in during that time, right? So I think, you know,
그리고 그 시기에 시대를 대표하는 기업들도 일부 탄생했습니다.
that's sort of almost inevitable. There'll be over exuberance, once everyone realizes how
그래서 이런 일은 거의 불가피합니다. 특정 기술이 얼마나 변혁적인지 모두가 깨닫게 되면 과열이 생기고,
transformative a specific technology is, and then there'll be a, probably a reckoning, and then the
아마 조정 국면도 오며, 그다음에는 실체가 있는 것들이 살아남아 번성할 것입니다.
things that are real will survive and flourish. Where, it seems to me, is, you know, maybe like
제게 특히 문제로 보이는 곳이 있습니다.
in the private markets, where there's sort of seed rounds, of 10s of billions of dollars,
예컨대 비상장 시장에서 수백억 달러 규모의 시드 라운드가 이뤄지고 있습니다.
where basically there's just almost nothing there yet, and that seems a little bit unsustainable
그런데 사실상 아직 거의 아무것도 없는 상태에서 그런 투자가 이뤄지기도 합니다.
over the long run. As far as I'm concerned, I don't really worry about bubbles. My point of
이는 장기적으로는 다소 지속 가능하지 않아 보입니다. 저는 거품 자체를 크게 걱정하지는 않습니다.
view is sort of leading Google DeepMind. I've got to make sure that whichever way it goes, whether
제 입장은 구글 딥마인드를 이끄는 입장에서, 어느 쪽으로 흘러가든 대비해야 한다는 것입니다.
it continues to go all rosy and exponential, like it is now, or there's a bubble that, you know,
지금처럼 모든 것이 장밋빛으로 기하급수적으로 계속되든,
there's some kind of bubble bursting, that we're in the right position to, to win either way,
어떤 형태로든 거품이 꺼지든, 어느 경우든 우리가 이길 수 있도록 올바른 위치에 있어야 합니다.
and to take advantage of that either way. And I think we've got a good position, given Google's
그리고 어느 쪽이든 그 상황을 활용할 수 있어야 합니다.
underlying business and how AI fits with that, to to to benefit, whichever way it goes from here.
그리고 구글의 기본 사업 구조와 그 안에서 AI가 어떻게 맞물리는지를 보면, 앞으로 어떤 방향으로 가든 혜택을 볼 수 있는 좋은 위치에 있다고 봅니다.
Some I guess some of your biggest competitors are the ones who have managed to raise huge sums
또 가장 큰 경쟁자들 가운데 일부는 현재까지 민간 시장에서 막대한 자금을 조달하는 데 성공한 기업들입니다.
of money in the private markets at this point. So do you feel confident that even if there is
그래서 설령 어느 시점에 어떤 조정이 오더라도, 버텨낼 수 있다고
some sort of correction at some point that, you know, you'll be able to weather it out I guess
확신하십니까?
Yeah I mean, look, you know, that's the whole point of Google's balance sheet, and also all
네, 그러니까요. 보십시오, 이게 바로 구글의 탄탄한 재무상태표가 존재하는 이유이고, 또
the incredible products that and surfaces that, that we have, you know, I think it's, you know,
우리가 보유한 놀라운 제품들과 서비스 접점들 덕분입니다. 제 생각에는,
dozens of multibillion user products and and AI kind of naturally fits into all of those products,
수십 개의 수십억 사용자 규모 제품들이 있고, AI는 자연스럽게 그 모든 제품에
whether it's, you know, email workspace or or, you know, new things like the Gemini app.
이메일 워크스페이스이든, 아니면 제미나이 앱 같은 새로운 것이든 적용될 수 있습니다.
Yeah, you mentioned dynamics at play as well. We talked competition. The other one is geopolitics,
네, 작용하는 역학도 언급하셨습니다. 경쟁을 이야기했고, 또 하나는 지정학입니다,
which you mentioned as well, when huge discussions around China, of course,
물론 중국을 둘러싼 큰 논의 속에서 말씀하신 부분이기도 합니다.
in this kind of competition battle between China and the US. But there was a point where
중국과 미국 간 이런 경쟁 구도에서 말입니다. 하지만 한때는 그런 시점이 있었습니다.
people were discounting the ability of China and its companies to come up with strong AI
사람들이 중국과 중국 기업들이 강력한 AI를 만들어낼 역량을 과소평가했습니다.
models and technologies. But actually we saw with kind of what Deep Seek did. It kind of brought a
모델과 기술을 말입니다. 그런데 실제로 딥시크(DeepSeek)가 한 일을 보면, 일종의
bit of shock to our but actually, more than that, some of the big tech companies like Alibaba,
충격을 줬습니다만, 사실 그보다 더 중요한 건 알리바바 같은 대형 테크 기업들이
coming up with some very competitive open source models. So China's not out of this game, right?
아주 경쟁력 있는 오픈소스 모델들을 내놓고 있다는 점입니다. 그러니 중국이 이 게임에서 빠진 것은 아니지 않습니까?
Not at all. And actually, you know, I think they are closer to the US front, you know,
전혀 아닙니다. 그리고 사실 제 생각엔 그들이 미국의 최전선, 그러니까
US and West Frontier models, than maybe we thought one or two years ago. Maybe
미국과 서방의 프런티어 모델들에 우리가 1~2년 전 생각했던 것보다 더 가까워졌습니다. 어쩌면
they're only a matter of months behind at this point. The interesting thing is,
지금은 몇 달 정도만 뒤처져 있는 수준일 수도 있습니다. 흥미로운 점은,
and they're very there's from very capable teams, of course, like the deep seek team and Alibaba you
그리고 물론 딥시크 팀이나 말씀하신 알리바바처럼 아주 유능한 팀들이 있다는 점입니다. 그런데 질문은,
mentioned. And the question is, is, can they innovate something new beyond the frontier?
그들이 프런티어를 넘어서는, 그 너머의 새로운 무언가를 혁신할 수 있느냐는 것입니다.
So I think they've shown they can catch up, you know, and be very close to the frontier
그래서 저는 그들이 따라잡을 수 있고, 프런티어에 아주 가까이 갈 수 있다는 걸 보여줬다고 생각합니다.
and catch up very quickly. But can they actually innovate something new, like a new Transformers,
그리고 매우 빠르게 따라잡을 수도요. 하지만 실제로 새로운 트랜스포머 같은,
you know, that gets Beyond the Frontier? I don't think that's been shown yet.
그러니까 프런티어를 넘어서는 무언가를 만들어낼 수 있느냐는 아직 보여주지 못했다고 봅니다.
Is that going to be, in your view, difficult because of
그게 당신 보시기엔, 어렵게 만드는 요인이 있습니까?
restrictions on access to technology, like leading edge chips, for example?
예를 들어 최첨단 칩 같은 기술 접근 제한 때문입니까?
No, I think it's more a mentality issue, you know. So I think it's something that at least the
아니요, 저는 그보다는 사고방식의 문제라고 생각합니다. 그래서 적어도
leading. Labs, the leading frontier labs in the West have nurtured, I can say for ourselves, you
서방의 선도 연구소, 최전선 연구소들이 길러온 부분이고, 저희의 경우를 말씀드리면,
know, we, you can think of DeepMind as a bit like a try to be a modern day Bell Labs and encourage
딥마인드는 현대의 벨 연구소(Bell Labs) 같은 곳이 되려고 하면서, 알려진 것을 규모만 키우는 게 아니라
innovation and exploratory innovation, not just kind of, you know, scaling out what's what's known
혁신과 탐색적 혁신을 장려해 왔습니다. 그리고 물론 그런 일은 이미 매우 어렵습니다. 왜냐하면
today. And of course, that's already very difficult, because you need world class
오늘날 그걸 해내려면 세계적 수준의 공학 역량이 필요하기 때문입니다. 그리고 중국은 분명히 그걸 갖추고 있습니다. 질문은,
engineering already to be able to do that. And China definitely have that. The question is,
문제는 과학적 혁신 부분인데, 이것이 훨씬 더 어렵다는 것입니다.
is the scientific innovation part that's a lot harder to, you know, to invent something is about
즉, 무언가를 발명하는 것은,
100 times harder than it is to to copy it. So the question that's the next frontier release is,
그걸 복제하는 것보다 100배는 더 어렵습니다. 그래서 다음 프런티어에서의 질문은,
and I haven't seen evidence of that yet, but it's very difficult.
저는 아직 그런 증거를 보지 못했지만, 정말 매우 어렵다는 점입니다.
So one of the most striking parts of that part of the conversation for me, Steve was around China.
스티브, 그 대화에서 제게 가장 인상적이었던 부분 중 하나는 중국에 관한 얘기였습니다.
I used to live in China for just over three years. Report out of China for CNBC,
저는 중국에서 3년 조금 넘게 살았고, CNBC를 위해 중국에서 보도도 했습니다.
covering the tech sector there. And there was this growing view recently that actually China is so
그곳의 기술 분야를 취재했습니다. 그런데 최근 들어 실제로 중국이
far behind the US when it comes to AI for multiple reasons. One of those is that, oh, it may not be
여러 이유로 AI에서 미국보다 크게 뒤처졌다는 인식이 커졌습니다. 그중 하나는, 중국이
able to get its hands on the most advanced chips so its industry could fall behind. One view is
가장 첨단 칩을 손에 넣지 못해 산업이 뒤처질 수 있다는 것이었습니다. 또 다른 견해는
that it's just not innovating, and it doesn't have the capital the way US companies do. But actually
그저 혁신을 하지 못하고, 미국 기업들처럼 자본도 없다는 것이었습니다. 하지만 실제로
what was really interesting from Demis is he said that he believes Chinese AI models are just months
데미스의 발언에서 정말 흥미로웠던 점은 중국 AI 모델이 미국보다 불과 몇 달 정도만 뒤처져 있다고 믿는다고 했다는 것입니다.
behind where the US is, so actually not far behind. And remember when last year we had Deep
즉, 실제로는 크게 뒤처진 것이 아니라는 뜻입니다. 그리고 작년에 우리가 딥
Seek really shock the world and markets. It showed I think China is in the game. And since then,
시크가 전 세계와 시장을 정말 충격에 빠뜨렸던 것을 기억하실 겁니다. 그건 중국도 이 경쟁에 참여하고 있음을 보여줬다고 생각합니다. 그리고 그 이후로,
whilst Deep Seek hasn't quite made the waves, it did when it first kind of came out, Alibaba,
딥시크가 처음 나왔을 때만큼 파장을 일으키지는 못했지만, 알리바바는
one of the world's biggest or one of China's biggest tech companies, has been a leader there.
세계 최대급이자 중국 최대급 기술 기업 중 하나로서 그 분야의 선두주자였습니다.
It's developed some really interesting models, which, if you look at the opensource communities,
매우 흥미로운 모델들을 개발해 왔는데, 오픈소스 커뮤니티를 보면,
such as on a site called Hugging Face, you see Alibaba's models are amongst some of the most
예를 들어 허깅페이스라는 사이트에서 알리바바의 모델들이 가장
popular experts who I've spoken to in the space say they're amongst some of the most advanced in
인기 있는 모델들 가운데 하나라는 것을 볼 수 있고, 제가 이 분야에서 대화한 전문가들은 그것들이 세계에서 가장
the world. So you are seeing there. And one of the things I can tell you, just from living and
첨단 수준 중 하나라고 말합니다. 그래서 그런 흐름이 보입니다. 그리고 제가 그곳에서 살며
working out there, is Chinese companies move fast. They have the expertise and they can innovate,
일해 본 경험으로 말씀드리자면, 중국 기업들은 움직임이 빠릅니다. 전문성도 있고 혁신도 할 수 있어서,
so you can't discount them out of this kind of AI race. But also, take Demis's point that he said,
이런 AI 경쟁에서 그들을 배제하고 생각할 수는 없습니다. 하지만 데미스가 말한 요점도 받아들여야 합니다.
whilst the Chinese companies are sort of catching up and are very much in this race,
중국 기업들이 따라잡고 있고 분명 이 경쟁에 뛰어들어 있지만,
one thing they haven't proven is their abilities to kind of make these big breakthroughs. So,
그들이 이런 대규모 돌파구를 만들어낼 능력을 아직 입증하지는 못했다는 점입니다.
you know, I thought that was a really interesting and nuanced view. I guess the other part here,
저는 그것이 정말 흥미롭고도 미묘한 관점이라고 생각했습니다. 그리고 또 다른 부분이 있습니다.
Steve is something you picked up on is Demis's comments on bubbles and AI bubbles.
스티브, 당신이 짚어낸 버블, 즉 AI 버블에 대한 데미스의 발언입니다.
Yeah, that, by the way, just talking, let's go back to what he said first, about the months
네, 그런데 우선 그가 말한 "몇 달" 얘기로 다시 돌아가보죠.
thing. Deep Seek a year ago. It wasn't just about the fact that China can do it and make a really
1년 전 딥시크는 중국도 해낼 수 있다는 점을 보여줬습니다.
good large language model or a chat bot. It was also the idea that they did it without the most
그것은 훌륭한 대규모 언어 모델이나 챗봇을 만들 수 있다는 사실만의 문제가 아니었습니다.
powerful Nvidia chips that kind of rattled the markets as well, and that's what we're seeing here
가장 강력한 엔비디아 칩 없이도 해냈다는 점이 시장을 흔들었고, 지금 우리가
in the United States now Arjun is trying to limit China's ability to get those Nvidia chips. There's
미국에서 보고 있는 것도 바로 그것입니다. 이제 아르준은 중국의 엔비디아 칩 접근을 제한하려고 합니다.
all this talk about maybe they'll get those H200 chips, which aren't the best chips, but they're
최고 성능은 아니지만 H200 칩을 얻을지도 모른다는 얘기도 나오고,
better, probably than what China has access to. And then you get into the whole smuggling thing.
그러다 보면 결국 밀수 문제까지 거론되게 됩니다.
But to Demis's point, you know, if they really are months behind without full access to these chips,
하지만 데미스의 요점대로, 그런 칩들에 완전히 접근하지 못한 상태에서도 정말 몇 달 차이라면,
you know, that kind of questions Nvidia's prominence and dominance in the chip space as
이는 칩 분야에서 엔비디아의 두드러짐과 지배력에도 의문을 제기하게 됩니다.
well. But yes, what you said about the bubble is also super interesting too, because you asked him
그리고 네, 버블에 대해 말씀하신 부분도 매우 흥미롭습니다. 왜냐하면 당신이 그에게
about that, are we in a bubble? What do you think all this sort of things. And he basically said,
"우리는 지금 버블에 있는 건가요?" 같은 질문을 했고 여러 가지를 물었는데, 그는 기본적으로 이렇게 말했습니다.
we're Google. We're rich. It doesn't matter. We have the money. We have the free cash flow to
"우리는 구글입니다. 우리는 부자입니다. 상관없습니다. 우리는 돈이 있고, 자유현금흐름이 있어서
spend this our balance sheet is our superpower. If for some reason we need to rein back the spending,
이런 데에 지출할 수 있습니다. 우리 대차대조표가 우리의 초능력입니다. 어떤 이유로든 지출을 줄여야 한다면,
we can do it and we'll be fine. But guess who can't do that? That's OpenAI and Anthropic,
우리는 그렇게 할 수 있고 괜찮을 겁니다. 하지만 누가 그렇게 못할까요? 오픈AI와 앤스로픽입니다.
the other two leaders, X ai, we can throw them in here too. Their whole thing is they have to
또 다른 선두주자인 xAI도 여기에 포함할 수 있는데요.
raise money indefinitely in order to get to the point where they can finally show some revenue
이들의 처지는, 결국 매출을 보여줄 수 있는 지점에 도달할 때까지 끝없이 자금을 조달해야 한다는 점입니다.
and revenue growth to sustain themselves without continuous fundraising if things start to dry up,
그리고 지속적인 자금 조달 없이도 자생할 수 있을 만큼의 매출과 매출 성장도 보여줘야 합니다. 그런데 만약 자금줄이 마르기 시작하면 말입니다.
open AI and anthropic are at extreme risk, Google, Microsoft, meta, they have the cash
오픈AI와 앤스로픽은 극도로 위험해집니다. 반면 구글, 마이크로소프트, 메타는 현금흐름이 있습니다.
flow to move on to another project. Meta has already done it with the metaverse. These
그래서 다른 프로젝트로 옮겨갈 수 있습니다. 메타는 이미 메타버스로 그런 전환을 해봤습니다.
companies can pivot very easily because they had these big, high margin businesses already
이런 기업들은 이미 규모가 크고 마진이 높은 사업을 갖고 있었기 때문에 매우 쉽게 방향 전환을 할 수 있습니다.
Demis lot of people, I guess, forget how much of Google's AI capabilities come out from DeepMind
데미스, 많은 분들이 구글의 AI 역량 중 얼마나 큰 부분이 딥마인드에서 나오는지 잊는 것 같습니다.
and yourself and your teams. How do you work with Google? There's a lot of fascination around
그리고 본인과 팀에서 나온다는 점도요. 구글과는 어떻게 협업하시나요?
that. Does Sundar Pichai call you up one day? Say, Hey, Demis, we need this thing, or we have this
그 관계에 대한 관심이 큽니다. 어느 날 순다르 피차이가 전화를 해서 "데미스, 이게 필요해요"라든가, "이런
idea for Gemini or for some other AI product. Can you build it? How is that relationship?
제미니나 다른 AI 제품에 대한 아이디어가 있는데 만들 수 있나요?"라고 하나요? 그 관계는 어떤가요?
Yeah, so the last three years, we've combined everything together as into Google Deep Mind this,
네, 지난 3년 동안 우리는 모든 것을 통합해 '구글 딥마인드'로 만들었습니다.
this one entity that that that all the AI research at Google goes on in and it's a kind
구글의 모든 AI 연구가 이 한 조직에서 이뤄지며, 일종의 결합체입니다.
of combination of Google research, Google Brain and Deep Mind and and I run that group, and it's,
구글 리서치, 구글 브레인, 딥마인드를 합친 형태이고 제가 그 그룹을 이끌고 있습니다.
it's like the engine room of Google. You should think of it like that. So all the AI technologies
그리고 그것은 구글의 엔진실 같은 곳이라고 생각하시면 됩니다. 그래서 모든 AI 기술은
is done by this group, by our group, and then it's diffused across, you know, all of these incredible
이 그룹, 즉 우리 그룹에서 만들고, 그다음 구글 전반의 놀라운 제품들로 퍼져 나갑니다.
products right across Google. And the last couple of years, we've been building that backbone,
그리고 지난 몇 년 동안 우리는 그 기반을 구축해 왔습니다.
so not just the models, but also almost in we architecting the entire infrastructure of
모델뿐만 아니라 거의 구글의 전체 인프라를 설계해
Google so that it can, you know, these things can ship incredibly quickly. These models,
이런 것들을 믿을 수 없을 만큼 빠르게 출시할 수 있도록요. 이런 모델들은
it's almost sim ship to all the main surfaces. So, you know, when we release a new Gemini model,
거의 주요 접점 전부에 동시에 배포됩니다. 그래서 우리가 새로운 제미니 모델을 출시하면,
it's there the next day or the same day in search and and that's been going really well. I think I
다음 날이나 당일에 검색에도 적용되며, 그 과정이 매우 잘 진행되고 있습니다.
would say we really got into our groove with the 2.5 Gemini models. And for the last sort
제 생각에 제미니 2.5 모델에서 우리가 정말 리듬을 탔다고 말씀드릴 수 있습니다.
of year that's becoming really a smooth process now, and I think you'll see that more over the
그리고 지난 1년 정도 동안 그 과정이 이제 정말 매끄러운 프로세스가 되었습니다.
next next 12 months. And so, you know, we think of ourselves as the and describe ourselves sort
앞으로 12개월 동안 그런 모습을 더 보시게 될 겁니다.
of as the engine room for that. And you know, Sundar and I pretty much talk every day about
그래서 우리는 스스로를 그런 일을 하는 엔진실이라고 생각하고 그렇게 설명합니다.
strategic things and where should the technology go, and what does the wider Google need. And then,
그리고 순다르와 저는 거의 매일 전략적 사안, 기술이 어디로 가야 하는지, 더 큰 구글 조직에 무엇이 필요한지에 대해 이야기합니다.
you know, we adjust the roadmaps and the plans, you know, on a daily basis,
그리고 우리는 로드맵과 계획을 사실상 매일 조정합니다.
whilst keeping in mind the long term goals of, you know, getting to AGI first, fast and safely.
그러면서도 AGI에 가장 먼저, 빠르게, 그리고 안전하게 도달한다는 장기 목표를 염두에 둡니다.
So we should, we should expect more of the ability to come up with with new things,
그렇다면 앞으로는 새로운 것들을 더 많이 만들어낼 수 있을 것으로 기대해도 되겠습니까?
new AI tools and that be shipped across the Google portfolio,
새로운 AI 도구들이 구글 전 제품군에 걸쳐 출시되고 있습니다.
etc, because of that kind of change you've made in that relationship.
등등, 그 관계에서 그런 변화를 만들어내셨기 때문입니다.
Yes thats right. So it's an incredibly tight sort of iteration loop and and,
네, 맞습니다. 그래서 굉장히 촘촘한 반복 루프가 있습니다.
you know, we're all on the same tech stack and so on
아시다시피 저희는 모두 같은 기술 스택을 사용하고 있습니다.
A lot of what you're building is going into Google products, but I know kind
지금 구축하시는 것의 상당 부분이 구글 제품에 들어갑니다.
of covering companies like Samsung. You help companies like Samsung to build out some of
하지만 삼성 같은 회사를 취재하다 보면, 삼성 같은 회사들이 일부를 구축하는 데도 도와주십니다.
the AI tools within their smartphones, for example, and that kind of thing as well.
예를 들어 스마트폰 안의 AI 도구 같은 것들입니다.
Well, look, we work with a lot of partners as you, as you mentioned, you know, we're very proud of
네, 말씀하신 것처럼 저희는 많은 파트너와 일하고 있고, 그 점을 매우 자랑스럽게 생각합니다.
the fact that our technology selected by those partners because they see how capable it is and,
그런 파트너들이 저희 기술의 역량을 보고 선택해 준다는 점입니다.
and actually, you know, it comes to Samsung and other devices, I think there's really interesting
그리고 삼성이나 다른 기기 이야기로 넘어가면, 정말 흥미로운 부분이 있습니다.
way. I'm very interested in the idea of edge compute and and faster versions of these models
저는 엣지 컴퓨팅과 이런 모델들의 더 빠른 버전에 큰 관심이 있습니다.
working on these edge devices, be those phones, but also new devices like glasses that we're
그것들이 휴대전화 같은 엣지 기기에서 동작할 뿐 아니라, 저희가 작업 중인 안경 같은 새로운 기기에서도 동작한다는 점입니다.
working on. And, you know, partners like Warby Parker and the idea of smart glasses, and I think
그리고 워비 파커 같은 파트너들과 함께 하는 스마트 안경이라는 아이디어도 있습니다.
Google's worked on smart glasses for a long time, as you know, but I think that they, you know,
아시다시피 구글은 오랫동안 스마트 안경을 연구해 왔습니다.
finally we have the killer app, I would say, for it, which is this idea of a universal assistant,
하지만 이제 마침내 그에 대한 킬러 앱을 갖게 됐다고 말씀드릴 수 있는데, 그것이 바로 범용 어시스턴트라는 개념입니다.
and, and, and sort of helping you in your everyday life. And I think all the, all the,
그리고 일상생활에서 여러모로 도와주는 것입니다.
all the big device players are going to be interested in that type of technology.
그리고 저는 모든, 모든 대형 디바이스 업체들이 그런 유형의 기술에 관심을 가질 것이라고 봅니다.
Demis. We've only got a few minutes left but I do want to ask a little bit about I was a
데미스, 시간이 몇 분 남지 않았지만 조금 여쭤보고 싶습니다.
brand new tech reporter when Google bought Deep Mind 2014 I think it was a 400 million
저는 구글이 2014년에 딥마인드를 인수했을 때 막 기술 기자를 시작했습니다.
pound 100 million pound deal back then. So many people didn't know what you what you
당시 딜 규모가 4억 파운드, 아니 1억 파운드였던 것으로 기억합니다.
did. And why is Google buying this British company? What's going what's going on here?
그때는 많은 사람들이 무엇을 하는지 몰랐습니다. 왜 구글이 이 영국 회사를 사는 것인가, 무슨 일이 벌어지는 것인가 싶었습니다.
Do you ever look back to that and and think, oh, maybe we should have stayed independent at all.
가끔 그때를 돌아보며 '아, 우리가 독립적으로 남았어야 했나'라고 생각하신 적이 있습니까?
Yeah Or Are you happy with how things have turned out
아니면 지금까지의 결과에 만족하십니까?
Well, look, we I knew it's funny. So, so the the head of search at the time Alan Eustace,
네, 재미있는 이야기인데요. 당시 검색 부문 책임자였던 앨런 유스타스가 있었습니다.
he was sort of in charge with Larry. Larry was sponsoring, Larry Page was sponsoring the deal,
그는 래리와 함께 총괄했고, 래리 페이지가 그 딜을 후원했습니다.
as he was CEO at the time but Alan Eustace was delegated the head of search to kind of close
당시 래리 페이지는 CEO였고, 앨런 유스타스는 검색 책임자로서 딜 마무리 작업을 맡았습니다.
the deal. And I did tell Alan that this would be the most important acquisition Google ever made,
그리고 저는 앨런에게 이것이 구글이 한 인수 중 가장 중요한 인수가 될 것이라고 말씀드렸습니다.
which is, which is quite something, given they've, you know, there's YouTube and AdWords and other
유튜브나 애드워즈 같은 것들과 다른 인수들이 있었다는 걸 생각하면, 꽤 대단한 말입니다.
things that they previously acquired. But I kind of knew how important this was going to be, and
하지만 저는 이것이 얼마나 중요해질지 어느 정도 알고 있었습니다.
also how good a fit it was with Google's mission, which is organize the world's information,
또한 '세상의 정보를 정리한다'는 구글의 미션과 얼마나 잘 맞는지도 알고 있었습니다.
and AI is a very natural fit to that and organizing and understanding information. I mean,
AI는 그 미션, 즉 정보를 정리하고 이해하는 일에 매우 자연스럽게 들어맞습니다.
what better tool than AI for that. So I kind of knew that would be a natural fit. And we
그에 AI보다 더 좋은 도구가 어디 있겠습니까. 그래서 자연스러운 궁합이라고 생각했습니다.
sort of knew that this, you know, maybe it's now worth, I don't know, 100x 1,000x of, you know,
그리고 저희는 대략 이런 일이 벌어질 거라는 것은 알고 있었고, 지금은 뭐, 모르겠지만 100배, 1,000배쯤 가치가 됐을 수도 있다고 생각했습니다.
what, of what we sold it for. But the thing is, I wanted to get back to the science at the time and
하지만 그때 저는 과학으로 다시 돌아가고 싶었습니다.
push forward the research, which was still very nascent back in 2014 and, you know, fair play
연구를 더 밀고 나가고 싶었고, 2014년 당시에는 연구가 아직 매우 초기 단계였습니다.
to Google is they were one of the few companies in the world, I think that could recognize and
공정하게 말하면, 구글은 세계에서 몇 안 되는 회사 중 하나로, 제 생각엔 이걸 알아볼 수 있었습니다.
specifically Larry at the time, how important this technology was going to be, what it could become,
특히 당시의 래리는 이 기술이 얼마나 중요해질지, 무엇이 될 수 있을지,
and what we see it for it today. And I don't think we could have done the great work we did
그리고 오늘날 우리가 그것을 어떻게 보는지까지도 알아봤습니다.
with AlphaGo and Alpha Fold and all the science we've done and if we hadn't had their backing and
그리고 구글의 지원이 없었다면 알파고와 알파폴드, 그리고 우리가 해온 모든 과학적 성과를 그렇게 해내지 못했을 것이라고 생각합니다.
the amount of compute that they could bring to play. So I don't have any regrets at all.
그들이 제공할 수 있었던 컴퓨팅 자원 규모 덕분입니다. 그래서 저는 전혀 후회가 없습니다.
So Tech CEOs, AI CEOs, the new rock stars of the world. I've seen Jensen Huang here in Europe,
그렇다면 테크 CEO, AI CEO들이 이제 세상의 새로운 록스타라는 말씀이신가요? 유럽에서 젠슨 황을 본 적이 있습니다.
and the CEO of Nvidia, being followed around by everyone as well. Jensen,
엔비디아 CEO인 그가 모두에게 둘러싸여 따라다니는 모습도 봤습니다.
I think, said recently that you and him talk he had great things to say about nano banana,
젠슨은 최근에 두 분이 대화한다고 했고, 새로운 이미지 생성 도구인 나노 바나나에 대해서도
the new image generation tool, as well. What do you guys discuss?
아주 좋은 말을 했던 것으로 압니다. 두 분은 어떤 이야기를 나누십니까?
I mean, Jensen's great, you know, incredible pioneer, also somebody,
젠슨은 훌륭한 분입니다. 놀라운 개척자이고, 또한
you know, I admire him for sticking to his vision for 2030, years now, in fact, I first
제가 존경하는 점이, 20~30년 넘게 자신의 비전을 지켜왔다는 점입니다. 사실 저는 처음에
started using GPUs in the 90s on for gaming, of course, for writing graphics engines and physics
90년대에 게임을 위해 GPU를 쓰기 시작했습니다. 물론 그래픽 엔진과 물리 엔진을 만들기 위해서였습니다.
engines. So it's funny that it's come full circle to me that that, you know, my early gaming days,
그래서 제 초기 게임 시절이 이렇게 한 바퀴 돌아, 당시 밀어붙이던 하드웨어가 지금은 AI에 유용하다는 점이
even the hardware that was pushed then, is now useful for AI, ironically. But yeah,
아이러니하게도 흥미롭습니다.
we talk about, he's very interested in science and AI for science. And actually, you know,
저희는 과학, 그리고 과학을 위한 AI에 대해 이야기합니다. 그는 과학과 과학을 위한 AI에 매우 관심이 많습니다.
Alpha fold was trained on GPUs, so we and he loves Alpha fold and the work that we're doing,
알파폴드는 GPU로 학습되었고, 그는 알파폴드와 우리가 하고 있는 일을 정말 좋아합니다.
you know, in drug discovery. So we most, mostly talk about AI for science.
특히 신약 개발 분야에서요. 그래서 우리는 대부분 과학을 위한 AI에 대해 이야기합니다.
I know a lot of the data centers are built in Nvidia systems, but I know Google also has its
많은 데이터 센터가 엔비디아 시스템으로 구축된 건 알고 있는데, 구글도 자체적인
Tensor Processing Units, TPU chips. Is there any kind of competitive friendliness there?
TPU 칩, 즉 텐서 처리 유닛이 있잖아요. 그 사이에 어떤 경쟁적이면서도 우호적인 관계가 있습니까?
We're lucky. We have our own we love our TPUs. We generally use them internally for training our
저희는 운이 좋습니다. 자체 TPU가 있고, TPU를 정말 좋아합니다.
our best models. And actually we found there's a big demand for that from the elite AI teams
저희는 보통 내부적으로 최고의 모델을 학습시키는 데 이를 사용합니다. 그리고 사실 최정예 AI 팀들로부터 큰 수요도 확인했습니다.
who are trying to build large models or serve very large AI models. They're specifically built for
대형 모델을 만들거나 매우 큰 AI 모델을 제공하려는 팀들입니다. TPU는
that. So TPUs are sort of they're a little bit more special case than GPUs. You can think of
바로 그런 목적을 위해 특별히 설계되었습니다. 그래서 TPU는 GPU보다 조금 더 특수한 용도라고 할 수 있습니다.
GPUs as being more general. So, you know, maybe we would use a GPU when we're trying to explore some
GPU는 더 범용적이라고 생각하시면 됩니다. 그래서 예를 들어 우리가
new architecture, like alpha fold was, or some new application. But then once we're when we're trying
알파폴드처럼 새로운 아키텍처나 새로운 응용을 탐색하려 할 때는 GPU를 사용할 수도 있습니다. 하지만
to sort of scale to the maximum, things we know, then, you know, custom silicon can be a lot more
최대한으로 스케일을 올려 우리가 아는 것들을 극대화하려 할 때는, 맞춤형 실리콘이 훨씬 더
efficient. So we're lucky. We have, we have both. We get to use both here at at Google and DeepMind,
효율적입니다. 그래서 저희는 운이 좋게도 둘 다 갖고 있고, 구글과 딥마인드에서 둘 다 사용할 수 있습니다.
Great Demis. Just looking to the future. You're obviously so focused on science and the potential
좋습니다, 데미스. 미래를 바라보면 과학과 그 잠재력에 매우 집중하고 계시지요.
for AI to create new drug breakthroughs. Do discover new diseases. Lots of potential
AI가 신약 개발의 새로운 돌파구를 만들고 새로운 질병을 발견할 잠재력도요. 가능성이 정말 큽니다.
things there. You've also got isomorphic labs, of course, as well. Where are we on this path to your
물론 아이소모픽 랩스도 운영하고 계시고요. 이러한 비전으로 가는 길에서 지금 우리는
your vision of AI unlocking all of these, these kind of breakthroughs in the world of science.
AI가 과학 분야의 이런 돌파구들을 열어내는 비전까지, 어디쯤 와 있습니까?
Well, look, I love, I always point to Alpha fold as probably the best example so far of AI applied
글쎄요, 저는 지금까지 AI가 과학에 적용된 최고의 사례로 아마 AlphaFold를 항상 꼽습니다.
to science. You know, I'm very proud of that project. And, you know, we solved a 50 Year
그 프로젝트가 정말 자랑스럽습니다. 그리고, 아시다시피, 저희는 50년
grand challenge in science of protein folding, how the structure of the structure of proteins,
동안 이어진 단백질 접힘(폴딩)이라는 과학의 거대한 난제, 즉 단백질 구조가 어떻게
and over 3 million researchers around the world are using it in their critical work.
형성되는지를 풀어냈고, 전 세계 300만 명이 넘는 연구자들이 핵심 연구에 이를 사용하고 있습니다.
So I can't imagine a more transformative sort of technology. And what I would love is to see have
그래서 이보다 더 혁신적인 기술은 상상하기 어렵습니다. 그리고 제가 정말 보고 싶은 것은
be able to point to a dozen Alpha Folds, and you know, each of them revolutionizing their area of
AlphaFold 같은 사례를 열두 개쯤 더 들 수 있게 되는 것이고, 각각이 자신의 분야를
science or mathematics. And I think we're well on the way to that. And we're working on half
과학이나 수학에서 혁신하는 것입니다. 저는 우리가 그 방향으로 잘 가고 있다고 생각합니다.
a dozen projects like that, in material science, in physics, in in maths, in weather prediction and
그리고 저희는 재료과학, 물리학, 수학, 기상 예측 등에서 그런 프로젝트를 대략 여섯 개 정도 진행하고 있고
and I think that the next 10 years, if, if AI, goes well and progress as well,
그리고 앞으로 10년 동안 AI가 잘 되고 진전도 순조롭게 이어진다면,
and we use it in the right way, could usher in a new golden age of scientific discovery.
그리고 우리가 이를 올바르게 사용한다면, 과학적 발견의 새로운 황금기를 열 수 있다고 생각합니다.
What do you think are going to be the big things in AI in 2026 any big breakthroughs,
2026년에 AI에서 큰 변화는 무엇이 될 것이라고 보십니까, 어떤 큰 돌파구가,
any big progresses that you think will happen?
어떤 큰 진전이 일어날 것이라고 생각하십니까?
Agentic system, systems able to do things more autonomously,
에이전틱 시스템, 즉 더 자율적으로 일을 할 수 있는 시스템들이
are going to start becoming reliable enough to be useful. I think we're going to see some
유용할 만큼 충분히 신뢰할 수 있는 수준이 되기 시작할 것입니다. 그리고 저는 우리가
really interesting things in robotics in the next 12 to 18 months, we're working really
향후 12~18개월 안에 로보틱스에서 정말 흥미로운 것들을 보게 될 것이라고 생각합니다. 저희는
hard on some very ambitious projects with Gemini robotics. And then finally, maybe,
제미니 로보틱스와 함께 매우 야심찬 프로젝트들을 열심히 진행하고 있습니다. 그리고 마지막으로, 아마도,
you know, AI systems on devices, I think we're going to start seeing them really useful in the
기기 안에서 동작하는 AI 시스템도 실제 세계에서 정말 유용하게 쓰이는 모습을 보기 시작할 것이라고 봅니다.
real world. And then maybe the thing I'm most excited about is advancing world models further,
그리고 제가 가장 기대하는 것은 월드 모델을 더 발전시키는 것입니다,
making them more efficient so they can actually be used, maybe for planning in our general models.
효율을 높여 실제로 활용할 수 있게 만드는 것이지요. 어쩌면 범용 모델에서 계획 수립에 쓰일 수도 있습니다.
Great. Demis, I'm going to take that last answer as a sort of teaser trailer for the next time you
좋습니다. 데미스, 방금 마지막 답변은 다음에 우리가 다시 만날 때를 위한 일종의 티저 예고편으로 받아들이겠습니다.
and I get to catch up, hopefully at some point this year. Thank you so much for joining me.
올해 어느 시점엔가 다시 이야기 나눌 수 있길 바랍니다. 함께해 주셔서 정말 감사합니다.
Thank you. Thanks for having me That's good. Then we'll get back
감사합니다. 초대해 주셔서 감사합니다
into the chat. Great. There's just the final part, yeah, yeah, yeah, and
대화에 불러주셔서요. 좋습니다. 이제 마지막 부분만 남았네요, 네, 네, 네, 그리고
So Steve, just in that final part of the conversation, I thought what was interesting
스티브, 대화의 마지막 부분에서 흥미로웠던 점은
is the relationship between kind of the Deep Mind entity and the broader Google business. And there
딥마인드라는 조직과 더 넓은 구글 비즈니스 사이의 관계였습니다. 그리고
was a part where Demis was saying he speaks to Sundar Pichai, the CEO of Google, or Alphabet,
데미스가 구글, 혹은 알파벳의 CEO인 순다르 피차이와
every day and and how sort of more integrated they've become, I think, if I'm thinking about
매일 대화한다는 점과 두 조직이 얼마나 더 통합되어 왔는지였는데요. 이 AI 경쟁을 생각해보면,
that this AI race, what that signals to me is that Google has clearly. Figured out how to become
제게 시사하는 바는 구글이 분명히 AI 제품을 시장에 빠르게 내놓는 법을 터득했다는 점입니다.
speedy at getting AI products to market. But also you got to think about all these Google products
하지만 크롬이든 지메일이든 무엇이든, 이런 모든 구글 제품들을 생각해보셔야 합니다.
right, whether it's Chrome, whether it's Gmail, whatever it might be they are wanting, whatever
그들이 개발하는 구글 AI가 모든 제품 전반에 확산되길 원하고 있고, 이는
Google AI is being developed to spread all across, all across those products that gives them an
그렇게 되면 일부 제품을 통해 거의 즉시 활용할 수 있는 사용자 기반을 갖게 되는데,
absolutely mammoth user base to kind of almost instantly tap into with some of these products.
이런 일부 제품으로 거의 즉각적으로 활용할 수 있는 정말 거대한 사용자 기반이 있습니다.
And I've always, I've said this for a while now, I think one of Google's biggest strengths,
그리고 저는 늘, 꽤 오래전부터 말해왔는데, 구글의 가장 큰 강점 중 하나는
really, is that when you think about the Android operating system and and you know how large it is,
사실 안드로이드 운영체제를, 그리고 그것이 얼마나 거대한지 떠올려보면,
70% odd market share globally, you know that is a huge amount of people and devices where
전 세계 시장점유율이 70% 안팎인데, 이는 엄청난 규모의 사람들과 기기들이라는 뜻이며
Google AI could be instantly, effectively installed on and used quickly. So they're
그 위에 구글 AI를 사실상 즉시 설치해 빠르게 사용할 수 있습니다. 그래서
in a good position in terms of going to market, I think. And clearly, this relationship between
저는 이들이 시장에 내놓는 측면에서 유리한 위치에 있다고 봅니다. 그리고 분명히, 딥마인드와
Deep Mind and the broader Google business is going to be integral for Google to sustain
더 넓은 구글 사업 전반 사이의 이 관계는 구글이 지속적으로
any success over the over the longer run here Yeah, and on the Android front alone, I mean,
장기적으로 어떤 성공이든 유지하는 데 핵심이 될 것입니다.
Samsung, the biggest manufacturer of Android phones, they're already putting Gemini is
안드로이드 폰의 최대 제조사인 삼성은 이미 제미니를
their main chat bot. Gemini is their main AI. I was a little surprised. Samsung didn't try
자사의 메인 챗봇이자 메인 AI로 탑재하고 있습니다. 저는 조금 놀랐습니다. 삼성이
to build their own, which, like they have in the past, but No, they've completely gone all
예전처럼 자체 모델을 만들려 하지 않았다는 점입니다. 그런데 그렇지 않았고, 그들은 완전히
in on Gemini. They're partnering with Google on those the new mixed reality headset that
제미니에 올인했습니다. 또한 구글과 협력해 새 혼합현실 헤드셋도
they have. There are some upcoming glasses that they're working on in partnership, also
함께 개발하고 있습니다. 또 협업으로 개발 중인 안경도 곧 출시될 예정이며,
with companies like Warby Parker to design them. So yeah, Samsung is, like, really adopted this,
워비 파커 같은 회사들과도 함께 디자인하고 있습니다. 그래서 삼성은 이를 적극적으로 채택했고,
and that is a huge platform for Gemini, just just that, just the Samsung angle of it, just that huge
이것만으로도 제미니에겐 거대한 플랫폼입니다. 삼성이라는 측면만 보더라도, 그 자체로도 그 엄청난
market share they already have is great. And then let's talk about Apple. Gemini is actually going
기존 시장점유율이 매우 큽니다. 그리고 이제 애플에 대해 이야기해보겠습니다. 제미니는 실제로
to be the engine that powers this new version of Siri we're expecting in just a couple months time.
불과 몇 달 뒤에 공개될 것으로 예상되는 새 버전의 시리를 구동하는 엔진이 될 것입니다.
He did talk about his excitement to see Gemini kind of spread on more devices. So I think it's
그는 제미니가 더 많은 기기로 확산되는 것을 보게 될 것에 대한 기대도 언급했습니다. 그래서 저는
a really smart move by Apple to kind of realize it can't build this on its own and honestly do
애플이 이를 자체적으로 구축할 수 없다는 점을 인식하고, 솔직히
what Samsung is doing, and say, Okay, let's just integrate this proven technology. We already have
삼성이 하는 것처럼 “좋습니다, 검증된 이 기술을 그냥 통합하자”라고 한 것은 정말 현명한 판단이라고 봅니다. 우리는 이미
a great relationship with Google. And this is honestly a different kind of Google that I've
구글과 훌륭한 협력 관계가 있습니다. 그리고 솔직히 이것은 제가
been seeing, that I've seen for so many years, where you had so many different groups kind of
수년 동안 보아왔던 구글과는 다른 모습입니다. 예전에는 서로 다른 많은 팀들이
working on the same thing. I mean, before this big reorg, and Demis got all that control over
같은 일을 하고 있었습니다. 즉, 이 대규모 조직 개편 이전에는, 데미스가 AI 전반에 대한 통제권을 갖기 전에는
all of AI. There were multiple groups within Google working on artificial intelligence, kind
구글 내부에 인공지능을 다루는 여러 그룹이 있었고,
of bumping against each other. And Sudar Pichai was really smart saying we got to, this is a huge
어느 정도 서로 부딪치고 있었습니다. 그런데 순다르 피차이는 “우리는 해야 합니다, 이건 정말 큰
moment. We got to reorganize everything. He folded everything under Demis, and put it into Deep Mind,
순간입니다. 모든 것을 재정비해야 합니다”라고 말하며, 모든 것을 데미스 아래로 통합해 딥마인드로 옮겼고,
and that's where we are now. And it's really paid off in 2025 in a big way with Gemini three.
그 결과가 지금의 상황입니다. 그리고 2025년에 제미니 3로 큰 성과를 거뒀습니다.
Yeah, and that consumer space really is getting more and more intense when it comes to the the AI
네, 그리고 소비자 시장에서는 AI 측면에서 경쟁이 점점 더 치열해지고 있습니다.
side of things, particularly, as you know, you mentioned before when you were talking
특히, 앞서 거품 이야기와 관련해 말씀하셨듯이,
about some some of the talk about bubbles, these competitors, like Open AI, you know, Google has
오픈AI 같은 경쟁자들이 있고, 구글은
big balance sheet, strong cash flow, and it has a huge user base of users, and continues
튼튼한 재무상태표와 강한 현금흐름을 갖고 있으며, 막대한 사용자 기반이 있고, 계속
to innovate. And I think this really does, given that kind of, that reorg, and this kind of speed
혁신하고 있습니다. 그리고 그런 조직 개편과 지금 구글이 보여주는 속도를 감안하면,
you're seeing now from Google, I think this is adding, going to add a lot of competitive
이것이 상당한 경쟁
pressure onto open AI, particularly on the consumer side in 2026 so it's all up for grabs.
압박을 오픈AI에 가할 것이라고 봅니다. 특히 2026년 소비자 분야에서는 모든 것이 열려 있습니다.
Yeah, and we're going to see a lot of different stuff. I anticipate from open AI this year.
네, 그리고 우리는 정말 다양한 것들을 보게 될 것입니다. 저는 올해 오픈AI가
They're going to throw all the spaghetti at the wall they can to see what sticks,
될 만한 것은 무엇이든 다 시도해 보며 무엇이 통하는지 보려 할 것이라고 봅니다,
because they've put enormous pressure on themselves to generate enormous amounts of
왜냐하면 그들은 엄청난 규모의
revenue in order to fulfill all of these promises they made about capital expenditure build out of
매출을 만들어내야 한다는 압박을 스스로에게 걸어, 자본지출로
these big data centers with Oracle and all these sorts of things like that,
오라클과 함께 이런 대형 데이터센터를 구축하겠다는 약속 등
it cannot happen all these committed spending they have unless they productize it better and
이미 확정한 지출을 더 잘
more effectively. But like to your point, we're seeing this with meta. By the way,
제품화하고 더 효과적으로 만들지 않으면 실현될 수 없기 때문입니다. 하지만 말씀하신 대로 메타에서도 이런 모습을 보고 있습니다. 참고로,
Meta has a huge opportunity to leverage its user base. And it hasn't figured out how to do that
메타는 자사의 사용자 기반을 활용할 큰 기회가 있지만, 그걸 어떻게 할지
in the way Google has. So right now, Google feels like they're kind of on top of things.
구글처럼 해내지는 못했습니다. 그래서 지금은 구글이 대체로 우위를 점하고 있는 느낌입니다.
Well, look, part two of this miniseries on Deep Mind is going to be out next week,
딥마인드 미니시리즈 2부는 다음 주에 공개될 예정이고,
and we're speaking to Lila Ibrahim, who is the COO over at DeepMind. So catch that. And
딥마인드의 COO인 릴라 이브라힘과 이야기를 나눌 예정이니 꼭 확인해 보시기 바랍니다. 그리고
if you've got any comments or thoughts about this episode, please reach out to us. You can
이번 에피소드에 대한 의견이나 생각이 있으시면 저희에게 연락해 주십시오.
reach us pretty much everywhere. I think You're on multiple social media platforms
거의 어디서든 저희에게 연락하실 수 있습니다. 여러 소셜미디어 플랫폼에 계시잖아요.
I'm a blue sky guy. I'm a blue sky guy
저는 블루스카이를 이용합니다. 저도 블루스카이를 이용합니다.
Yeah, we're all over the place.
네, 저희는 정말 여기저기 다 있습니다.
I quit Instagram seven and a half years ago, and I do not regret it.
저는 7년 반 전에 인스타그램을 그만뒀는데, 전혀 후회하지 않습니다.
Wow, that's amazing. Yeah, no more Doom scrolling. Love it.
와, 대단하네요. 네, 이제 둠스크롤링은 끝입니다. 정말 좋습니다.
No more Doom scrolling for this guy
이분은 더 이상 둠스크롤링을 하지 않습니다.
Thank you all for listening and watching. We'll catch you next time you.
들어 주시고 시청해 주셔서 감사합니다. 다음에 또 뵙겠습니다.